【music】
【音乐】
good welcome
好 欢迎
Thank you for participating in this month's quiz
谢谢各位参加这个月的知识响验
Today our leader is
今天我们的主将者是
Researcher Zhao Guangyu
赵光玉研究员
Is a researcher at the Institute of Employment and Life Support
是本院职务及维生务学研究所的研究员
Dr. Zhao is a member of the National Central University Job Research Institute
赵博士是国立中心大学职务研究所
Graduate Master
毕业生硕士
PhD
博士
Zhuo Shi
卓士
Sui Shi and Zhuo Shi are there
隋士跟卓士在那里
Then go to the Union Campus of the University of California
然后到美国加州大学的合兵分校
This is the Riverside campus
这是Riverside分校
Dr. Duke Read
念公督博士
Got a doctorate degree in occupational science there
在那里拿到也是职务学的博士学位
Washington State University
后来到华盛顿州立大学
it's seattle
是西雅图
Bouman does Postal
布曼做Postal
Then
然后
in molecular biology
是在分子生物
Should be biochemistry
应该是生物化学
During this process, I have always been interested in the study of plants
这个过程中一直对植物的研究有兴趣
Returned to Zhongyuan Hospital in 1999
1999年回到中原院
Joined the Phytomachine Microbiology Institute team
加入了植物机 微生物学研究所团队
it is now a researcher at the institute
它现在是该所的研究员
And the deputy director
还有是副所长
director here
所长在这里
yes we are
对 是我们是
The Botanical Sanitation Institute belongs to the Central Plains
植物卫所是中原的
In the life sciences, it is the first
在生命科学的话是第一所
Yes, the land here used to be the land of the Botanical Guard
对 以前这边的土地都是植物卫所的土地
our side too
我们这边也是
Later, it was given to us by us, it seems like this
后来是我们团团给我们的 好像是这样子
right
对
So its research work in plant reproduction
所以它的研究工作在植物的生育
There are many studies on the process of growth
跟生长的过程都是有很多的研究
have very good grades
有非常好的成绩
Today he will share with us
今天他會跟我們分享一下
It is using genetic technology
就是在用基因學的技術
To understand the growth process of plants
對瞭解植物的生育生長過程
OK, then we welcome Dr. Zhao Guangyu
好 那我們歡迎趙光玉博士
Thank you, Vice President Liu, for your introduction
謝謝劉副院長的介紹
first of all i want to thank you
首先我要謝謝
I would also like to thank the secretary of the headquarters for giving me this opportunity
也謝謝院本部的秘書助給我這個機會
Let me share with you the past period of time that we have
跟大家來分享我們過去這一段時間以來
in botany
在植物學方面
Especially the research on the reproductive growth of plants
尤其植物的生殖生長上面的研究
More importantly, thank you all for coming today
更重要是謝謝各位今天來
i know tonight
我知道今天晚上
You're probably all going to class
你們可能都要上課班上課
come back later
以後再過來
I try to keep this content from being too old
我盡量讓這個內容不會太古早
So this time we start today
所以這個時候開始我們今天
Basically, our laboratory mainly does
基本上我們實驗室主要是做
reproductive growth of plants
有關植物的生殖生長
And that's what I've always been interested in
然後這也是我一直有興趣的
Before we introduce plant reproductive growth
在我們介紹植物生殖生長之前
Let me introduce you first
我先各位介紹一下
There is a typical plant cell
有一個典型的植物的細胞
plant cells and animal cells
植物的細胞跟動物細胞
The biggest difference is
最大的不同的是
it has leaves
它有葉立體
it has cell arms
它有細胞臂
and most importantly
還有最重要
it has a large cell in the middle
它有中間有一個很大的細胞
vacuoles of cells
細胞的液胞
In addition there are many
另外還有許多的
protoplasmic contact wire
原生質的聯絡絲
So this plant cell
所以這個植物細胞
Can communicate with another plant cell
可以跟另外一個植物細胞
Through this protoplasmic connecting thread
透過這個原生質的聯絡絲
They can directly communicate with each other
它們可以直接互通訊息
The structure of the whole plant cell
植物整個細胞的結構
We can learn from molecules, loads, entrained gas
我們可以從分子、負荷物、包氣
cells all the way up to the whole plant
細胞一直最後到整個植物體
leaf filter
比如說葉濾素
They end up forming leaf filters
它們最後它們會構成葉濾體
The leaf filter is an air pocket inside the plant
葉濾體是植物裡面的一個包氣
Leaf filter eventually it will become
葉濾體最後它會變成
mesophyll cell
所謂的這個葉肉細胞
Post-leaf cells can shape light and function
葉後細胞可以形光和作用
finally forming a leaf
最後形成一個葉子
This is a construction of a whole plant
這是一個整個植物的一個構造
Our genes for the whole inside of the plant
我們對於植物的整個裡面的基因
mutant strains
影響主要是有突變株
You have a mutation in a single gene
你單單一個基因發生突變
Will affect the plant a lot of changes
會影響到植物很大很大的變化
For example, this is inside a tomato
比如說這個在番茄裡面
a gene that you overexpress
你去大量表現的某一個基因
like this gene it controls the leaves
像這個基因它會控制葉子
and leaflet development
還有小葉的發育
It turned out to be like this
原來是這樣子
you can make it like this
你可以讓它變成這樣子
Therefore, through such a control
所以可以經由這樣子的一個調控
to express to change a plant's
來表現來改變植物的一個
The pattern of growth and even its function
生長的型態 甚至它的功能
We all know planting
我們都知道種植
All kinds of planting
各式各樣種植
In fact, I also caught it from the Internet, and I don't know much about it.
其實我也從網路上抓的我也不太知道
The only thing I saw was this kind of osmanthus seeds
我唯一看了這個有點像桂瓜子
Other various plantings
其他的各式各樣種植
Planting is an important part of plants
種植是植物很重要的一部分
Why is it other than family reception
為什麼 它除了傳宗接待以外
It is also a food for many animals
它更是很多動物的一個食物
But the whole crop produces
但是整個種植的產生
Must have very successful reproductive growth
必須要有非常成功的生殖生長
So our content today
所以我們今天內容
I will divide it with you and you into these
我會跟大家跟各位分為這幾個
First, let me tell you about the reproductive system of plants
第一個跟各位介紹一下植物的生殖體系
The second one I will introduce to you
第二個我會跟各位介紹一下
In the past twenty years we have
我們在過去這一二十年
There is something new about the development of a molecular biology cytology tool
有一些新的一個分子生物學細胞學的工具的發展
So how do we use these
那我們怎麼樣去利用這些
we can explore
我們可以來探索
Some questions we may not have been able to explore before
我們以前可能沒辦法探索的一些問題
Finally, I will share with you our research work
最後我會跟各位分享一下我們的研究的工作
This is a reproduction of the whole angiosperm
這是整個被子植物的一個生殖
a life history
一個生活史
Angiosperms differ from other plants in that
被子植物跟其他的植物的不同是
generations of its counterparts
它的配植體的世代
Generations of so-called monoquilts
所謂的單被體的世代
very very short
非常非常的短
For example, this is the male reproductive organs
比如說這是雄性生殖器官
female reproductive organ male is anther
雌性生殖器官雄性就是花藥
Then the female word is
然後雌性的話就是
match it in the fat
配株它在脂肪裡面
Then when the anther goes through a split
然後在這個花藥經過一個分裂的時候
produce pollen
會產生花粉
androgenic plant
花粉是雄配植體
So its implant body stage
所以它的配植體世段
just a very short time
就非常短的一個時間
Then the embryo sac of the embryo pig
然後胚豬這個胚囊
It is the body of the partner
它就是持配之體
it has eggs in it
它裡面有卵
and finally
還有最後
When there is a so-called thin powder effect
當有所謂的瘦粉作用的時候
pollen hall
花粉館
From this pollen will be produced the pollen hall
從這個花粉會產生花粉館
Finally put it two fine packages
最後把它兩個精細包
Sent to embryonic pigs to complete double lean muscle
送到胚豬裡面完成雙重瘦筋
it's a whole process
這是一個整個過程
The last skinny egg
最後這個瘦筋卵
it will continue to develop into a planting
它就會再繼續發育成為一個種植
This is a life history of the whole plant
這是整個植物的一個生活史
so in
所以在
let's introduce
我們先介紹一下
whole plant reproductive system
整個植物的生殖體系
I will probably split it into two parts
我大概會分成兩個部分
introduce to you
跟大家介紹
The first is the sexual reproductive organs of plants
第一個是植物的有性生殖器官
It is the growth and differentiation of flower teeth
就是花牙的生長還有分化
For example, flower formation and structure
比如說花的形成還有結構
Huaya's clones and flower organs
花牙的分身組織還有花器
The second one will introduce to you
第二個會跟各位介紹
The so-called lean powder effect of plants
所謂的植物的瘦粉作用
these partners
就是這些配之體
For example, pollen and the formation of embryonic pigs
比如說花粉還有胚豬的形成
There is also the effect of the whole thin powder
還有整個瘦粉作用
So it's a process of selfing
所以它是自交的過程
Wait a minute and you'll know there's something good if you see me
等一下你看到我萬一要就知道有好東西
I want to introduce you to one
我要跟各位介紹的一個
This is an experimental material we made
這是我們做的一個實驗材料
called the Arab world
叫做阿拉伯界
Arab world
阿拉伯界
It's what we say in terms of our plants
它是我們在我們做植物方面來講的
so-called model plants
所謂的模式植物
like fruit flies or mice
像果蠅或者是小老鼠
or ant ants
或者是蝕蟻耿
These are model plants
這些它們是有模式植物
but we plant
但是我們植物
we are basically arabian
我們基本上是阿拉伯界
why it is
為什麼它是
its economy is very small
它的經濟非常小
The second its sequencing is done
第二個它的定序已經完成
The third
第三個
Because all the scientists all over the world
因為全世界所有的很多的科學家
use this as plant material
都以這個當作植物材料
So there are quite a few resources
所以有相當多的資源
or Internet information
或者網路的資訊
you can find
你可以找得到
Another one is
另外一個就是
it has many of us now
它在我們現在有很多的
so-called insertion with TDNA
所謂的用TDNA插入
mutants
所造成的突變株
it's okay i'll wait
沒關係這個我等一下
What is TDNA insertion?
各位介紹是什麼是TDNA插入
There are other mutants
還有其他的突變株
So when we have a mutant strain of this gene
所以我們當這個基因發生突變株
We know which gene it plugged in
我們知道它插壞了哪個基因
we see what it does
我們看到它有什麼性狀表現
We can probably infer the function of this gene
我們大概可以推測出來這個基因的功用
So genes get from this information
所以基因由這一些的資訊的獲得
So let it be over the past few years
所以讓它成為在過去這幾年
about ten years
大概十幾年以來
It makes a very nice plant material
它成為一個非常好的一個植物材料
We can study the genes of plants
我們可以研究植物的基因
participate in the development of, for example, pollen
參與的比如說花粉的發育
Or bear the growth of graft
或持熊配植體的生長
even pollination and seed growth
甚至受粉作用以及種子的生長
For a long time what we called
在長久以來我們所謂的
We all know that DNA is our genetic material
都知道DNA是我們的遺傳物質
It's a gene it makes a Mason
是基因它會做成Mason
Rapidly follow RNA and finally become protein
迅循RNA最後成為蛋白質
However, in past research we can find
但是在過去的研究我們可以發現
maybe it's not that simple
可能就不是那麼簡單了
Possibly RNA could also be a genetic material
可能RNA也可能是一個遺傳物質
For example, our teacher Lin Nazhen
比如說我們所得林納珍老師
The so-called headquarters he discovered
他發現的所謂的那個本部
Bamboo coelovirus
就是竹子的腔腔病毒
it is RNA
它是RNA
but it can be reversed into DNA
但是它可以反轉弄成為DNA
Then turn into RNA and donate into protein
然後再變成RNA再捐成蛋白質
This is a
這是一個
Another current study found that the so-called
另外一個現在研究發現所謂的
Generics related to production
表關與生產的Generics
none of your genes will change
你的基因都不會改變
you may see through your
你可能透過你的
change your DNA
改變你的DNA的
fake plan
的假計畫
or something in your DNA
或者是你DNA上面的一些
protein with it
蛋白質跟它
False project of binding protein
結合的蛋白質的假計畫
Or use sexual expression to control
或者以性化來表來控制
gene expression
基因的表現
So it's not just us anymore
所以這不再是單單我們
It is common to think that such a situation
常見來認為這樣的情況
This is probably a cartoon
這個大概是一個卡通
The picture can tell you about
圖片可以告訴你大概
how does the gene go
基因怎麼樣去
Execute and command
執行跟命令
Each of these is based on human genes
每一個這是以人類的基因來講
it has a nucleus
它都有個細胞核
cell nucleus in plant
植物裡面的細胞核
Another is the plant nucleus
再一個是植物的細胞核
Chromosomes inside
裡面有染色體
What about each of our chromosomes
我們每一個染色體呢
You see, this is equivalent to
你去看這相當於就是
the whole gene it winds a
整個基因它纏繞了一個
A protein called Histone
叫做Histone的一個蛋白質
This is the DNA
這上面就是DNA
DNA coils with
DNA纏繞上面有
these inherited messages
這些遺傳的訊息
we can call it gene
我們可以叫做基因
It then acts via detour
然後它經由轉路作用
it seems a little slow
它好像有點慢
that has a protein
那有一個蛋白質
It does this thing called DNA RNA polymerase
它會進行這個叫做DNA RNA polymerase
it opens up this genetic structure
它會把這個基因結構打開
Then started doing some messenger RNA
然後開始做了一些messenger RNA
Then the messenger RNA of these messages
然後這些訊息的messenger RNA
then start doing it slowly
然後就開始慢慢地做
It is a way to use ATGC to pair with each other
就是利用ATGC互相配對的一個方式
to allow it to produce a message RNA like this
讓它能夠產生這樣子的一個訊息 RNA
These last message RNA
最後這些訊息 RNA
and then at the end it goes through some chopping
然後最後它會經過一些切解
called messenger RNA
叫做messenger RNA
After the final cut
最後切解以後
it will start sending to the cytoplasm
它會開始送到細胞質
This is what it is in this cell
這個就是它在這個細胞
it cuts some
它會把一些切解
put some unwanted things
把一些不要的東西
Or we call intron to remove it
或者是我們叫做intron把它去掉
Finally turned into a function with
最後變成一個具有功能
It travels from the nucleus to the cytoplasm
它會從細胞核送到細胞質
Then in the cytoplasm it will be called by a
然後在細胞質它就會被一個叫做
ribexon the concrete
ribexon這個concrete
These two electric machines
這兩個電工機
Then it's called Rapidzone
然後它叫做Rapidzone
This is a ribose base structure
這是一個核糖底的構造
your message it goes along this
你的訊息它就沿著這個
The ribose base is right along the top
核糖底就沿著上面
there are different things
有不同的東西
Will put these Transfer RNA above
會把這些Transfer RNA上面
have brought a special IG nucleic acid
有帶來一個特別的IG核酸
It will recognize every Code
它會認識每一個Code
In this way, a protein is finally formed
就這樣最後形成了一個蛋白質
it's a whole process
這是整個的一個過程
so i think
所以我想
So the growth of the sexual biomass of the whole plant
所以整個植物的有性生質的生長
development we want to say
發育我們想說
The first is to introduce
第一個就是跟各位介紹
flowering of plants
植物的開花
its whole bloom
它的整個花氣
still formed
還有形成
whole plant regulator
整個植物的調控因子
probably the flowering of the plant
大概植物的開花
by two main factors
受到兩個主要的因子
an intrinsic factor
一個是內在因子
It means that plants must reach a certain stage
就是植物一定要到某一個階段
like all animals
就像所有動物
must be mature
一定要到成熟了
it can bloom
它才能夠開花
For example, these processes have gene expression for flowering
比如說這些過程有開花的基因表現
or hormonal control
或者是荷爾蒙的控制
Another external factor
另外一個是外在的因子
For example, to have
比如說要有
Length, such as photoperiod
長短 比如說光周期啦
or a low temperature
或者是有個低溫
The so-called vernalization effect
所謂的春化效應
The vernalization effect is mainly in the 1st and 2nd year
春化效應主要是在1、2年生的
what about a plant
一個植物呢
It must undergo a low temperature treatment in seedlings
它在幼苗必須要經過一個低溫的處理
later its plants will bloom
以後它的植物才會開花
throughout this process
在這整個過程中
From this picture you can find
由這張圖你可以發現
Whether it's biological clock, photoperiod, growth and delivery
不管是生物時鐘 光周期 生長發運
Finally, these messages will be
最後最後會把這些訊息
are concentrated in a few major ones
都集中在幾個主要的一個
gene above
基因上面
controlled by these genes
由這些基因去控制
Flower formation throughout the plant
整個植物的花的形成
The development of the whole flower is probably from
整個花的發育大概是從
the whole top the whole top of the branch
整個頂端 整個枝條頂端
All top inflorescence clones
最上面所有的花序分身組織
it will form this flower tooth clone
它會形成這個花牙分身組織
That is Flameris etc.
就是Flameris等
this is the inflorescence
這是花序
Then this is the clone with flower teeth
然後這是會有花牙的分身組織
Then grow with infinity
然後跟無限可以不斷生長的
For the branches of that plant
那個植物的枝條來講
Its flower teeth are basically limited growth
它花牙基本上是有限生長
when this place forms a flower
當這個地方形成一個花以後
it stops growing
它就會停止生長
So in the end, different flower vessels will be formed
所以最後會形成不同的花器
like, say, primitive cells
像比如說有原始細胞
Finally there are the primitive cells of this flower organ
最後有這個花器的原始細胞
finally form the whole flower
最後形成整個花
The structure of this flower is probably like this
這個花的構造大概是這樣
Let's talk about the model plant in the Arabian world
我們以阿拉伯界這個模式植物來講的話
It has about four from the outside to the inside
它由外而內大概有四個
There are four flowers
就是有四個花二
then there are four petals
然後有四個花瓣
But there are six stamens in the middle
但是中間有六個熊蕊
Finally in the middle are two fused cores
最後中間是兩個融合的磁蕊
it's a typical
這是一個很典型
everyone remember
大家記起來
wait a minute it will have a little quiz
等一下它會有一個小小的測驗
little quiz
小小的一個測驗
tell everyone
跟大家講
Genes involved in flowering flower buds
參與開花花芽的基因
For example, this gene that controls flower bud formation
比如說這個控制花芽形成的基因
There are two clones and flowers
有兩個分身組織還有花器
then or bowl
然後或者碗形
Bowl control over fat development
碗控制在脂肪發育的
And how do we know which genes
而且我們怎麼知道哪一些基因
control the whole process
控制這整個過程
The most important thing is the mutant strain we just talked about
最重要的就是我們剛剛講的突變株
When you have a mutation in one of your genes
当你某一个基因发生突变
You can find that the shape of the flower has changed
你可以发现花形状改变了
For example, it has more stamens
比如说它有比较多的熊蕊
or more petals
或是比较多的花瓣
you know the gene
你就知道这个基因
presumably involved in the process
大概是参与在这个过程
So many scientists
所以经有很多科学家
After slowly accumulating
慢慢累积起来以后
By now we probably know that there are
现在大概我们大概知道有像这样
This is the whole Arab world
这是整个阿拉伯界
From planting all the way to the whole flower
从种植一直到整个花
this way of planting
这道种植
such as controlling flower buds
比如说控制花芽
you don't want to go
各位不愿意去去
you just go to the Internet to check
你只要去网络上查
probably many
大概都有很多
Basically two types
大概基本上就是两类
The first is to promote the formation of flower bud differentiation tissue
第一个是促进花芽分化组织形成的
For example like LIFI
比如说像LIFI
or AP2
或者AP2
these things
这些东西
these genes
这些基因
Another one that maintains the flower buds into tissue
另外一个维持花芽分成组织的
Let's say this is the Arab world
比如说这是阿拉伯界
traditional one normal phenotype
传统的一个正常表现型
But you help you with a gene called LIFI
但是你帮你一个基因叫做LIFI
when like a leaf
像叶子一样的时候
it was originally supposed to be where the flower was
它原先应该是在花的位置
it becomes like a leaf
它就会变得像叶子
So you know why it's called LIFI
所以你知道为什么叫LIFI
LIFI is like a leaf
LIFI是像叶子一样的
flower tooth formation
這個基因是采取花牙形成
Also, for example, this
另外呢比如說這個
When you find out with another
當你跟另外一間發現的時候
it should stop flowering in this place
它應該這個地方花牙就應該停止
But with Dang LIFI and another
但是跟當LIFI跟另外一間
they keep growing
它們就不斷的生長
So you say that when these two genes can
所以你就說當這兩個基因可以
just under control
就控制的
This place should form a flower later
這個地方應該形成花以後
should stop
就應該停止
But when these two genes are mutated
但是當這兩個基因發生突變
it can keep growing
它可以不斷的生長
Another one like Terminal Flower
另外一個像Terminal Flower
That is to say, the gene
就是說這個基因
It just mutates there
它只要在那邊產生突變
there will be no such flowers
就不會有這個花去的產生
so this is a whole you can go and see
所以這是一個整個你可以去看到的
the first one so this is the control flower tooth
第一個所以這是控制花牙
But what about after the flower teeth are born?
但是花牙產生以後呢
there will be flowers
會有花器
flower organ
就花的器官
have a model
有一個model
Called ABC model
叫ABC model
is very famous
是非常的有名
look at
你看看
A gene controls the second round
A基因控制第二輪
flower vessel formation
花器的形成
A gene alone controls the first round
A基因單獨則控制第一輪
The B gene controls the formation of the second and third rounds
B基因控制第二三輪的形成
flower vessel formation
花器的形成
C gene controls third and fourth rounds
C基因控制第三四輪
A gene alone controls the fourth round
A基因單獨則控制第四輪
Resist each other
互相解抗
who can understand
誰看得懂
probably many do not understand
大概很多看不懂
But people use scientists to use this way
但是人家用科學家用這種方式
oh
哦
A gene alone controls the first round
A基因單獨的話控制第一輪
then B gene
然後B基因
B gene controls the first and second rounds
B基因控制第一二輪
second round
第二輪
So use something like this
所以用這樣子的
a mechanism for this
這個的一個機制
Then the C gene alone
然後C基因那單獨呢
Control is the fourth round
控制的是第四輪
Xiong Rui
就是所謂的熊瑞
But the A genes neutralize each other
但A基因互相解抗
That is, when the C gene is broken
也就是當這個C基因壞掉的時候
it occupies
它就佔據了
Gene A came running
A基因就跑過來了
Occupies the position of the A gene
佔據A基因的位置
remember
記得哦
ok let's take the test now
好 我們現在來考試
There will be prizes in the exam
考試就會有獎品
This is what I was looking for today
這個是我今天找
please us yesterday
昨天請我們所的
An administrator, Tingyu, he did it
一個行政人員庭裕他去做的
This is when our campus is open
這個是我們院區開放的時候
Shi Hulan's organization seconds
石湖蘭的組織秒
guessed right
猜對的 答對的
Answer the question correctly
問題答對的 又講
Okay, let's see when the A gene is mutated
好 我們看看當A基因發生突變了
what will happen to it
它會怎麼樣
so tell who can raise their hand
所以可以告訴誰可以舉手
tell me what the first round turns out to be
告訴我 第一個第一輪會變成什麼
what happens in the first round
第一輪會變成什麼
good
好
ok so what will it be
好 所以它會是什麼
Xiong Rui, Ci Rui, right?
熊蕊 慈蕊對不對
Okay, the second one, you raised your hand, you have to finish it
好 第二個呢 你舉手了 你要打完喔
What about the second round?
下第二輪呢
What is BC gold, what will mutual pursuit be
BC金那是什麼 相互追求會是什麼
BC Jin Xiongrui at any time, right?
BC金隨時熊蕊對不對
You have to tell me Xiongrui, Cirui, flower petals
你要告訴我熊蕊 慈蕊 花瓣
What about the third one?
第三個呢
good great fourth
好 很棒 第四個
Okay, so if you don't know what it grows like
好 所以你要不知道它生長什麼樣
So this is such a plant
所以這個是這樣的植物
Come on, Mr. Zhou, please help me to give it to him
來 周先生 麻煩你幫我給他好了
Okay, so you can find the words where the petals should be
好 所以你可以發現原先應該是花瓣的地方的話
it is now xiong rui
它現在變成熊瑞
So you can't tell it's not quite a flower at all
所以你看不出完全是不太像是一朵花的樣子
We have A B C three golds and two chances
我們有A B C 三個金 還有兩次機會
The second one, does anyone know when B gold has a mutation?
第二個 當B金發生突變的時候 有誰知道
what happens in the first round
第一輪會變成什麼
Hurry up, it's beautiful
趕快喔 很漂亮
It's been a long time today and it's blooming
今天這好久它有開花
Hands up, what's the first round?
舉手 來 第一輪是什麼
good second round
好 第二輪
third
第三
Xiong Rui
熊瑞
Fourth, well, I'll give you another chance
第四個 好 再給你是機會
Cirui good
慈瑞 好
OK this is the flower you think it looks like a flower
OK 這個是這朵花 你覺得它像一朵花
come to you
來給你
good third
好 第三個
last chance sorry
最後一次機會 對不起
only one left
只剩下一個
Advertise our position willing to open
廣告一下 我們職位所願去開放
every year there will be this
每一年都會有這個
Welcome to our office next year
歡迎大家明年來我們職位所
you can get it, you can get it
你就可以拿得到 可以換得到
Not getting it, it may take a little EVER to change it
不是拿到 可能需要花一點EVER去換
good third suck
好 第三個 吸精
When Sucking Mutations
當吸精發生突變
What would be the mutation A
發生突變A會是什麼
what's the first one at least raise your hand
第一個是什麼 至少舉手
good
好
flower two are you sure
花二 你確定
What about the second one?
第二個呢
Let's see what it looks like
你下面看這時候什麼樣的樣子
it's cool there are flowers in flowers
它很酷 花中有花
If you are running the original hydraulic power at home today
如果你今天你家裡是開的是原液電
Then you want to pre-summary
然後你們想要預總的話
This would be a great plant material
這會是一個很好的植物材料
Why
為什麼
it can only be bought like you
它只能像你買
you don't produce seeds
你不會產生種子
but there are flowers in your flowers
但是你花中又有花
isn't it beautiful
是不是很漂亮
it's a pretty good one
這是一個蠻不錯的一個
So this is the ABC gene
所以這是ABC基因
But scientists never give up
但是科學家永遠不會放棄
never satisfied
永遠不會滿足
they think so
他們覺得這樣
Because after you mutate all the ABC genes
因為你把ABC基因全部突變以後
but put it all in the plant
但是全部把它在植物裡面
everyone has performance
大家有表現
you didn't turn it into a flower
你沒有幫它變成一朵花
later they found out
之後他們發現了
BC gene
BC基因
when it's going to work
它如果要正常工作的時候
they will find
他們會發現
There is another group of genes
還有另外有一群基因
called SEP-123
叫做SEP-123
These three genes are very similar
這三個基因很像是
they are going to work together
他們要一起去工作
When your three genes
當你這三個基因
After SEP-123 is mutated
SEP-123都發生突變以後
The whole plant will turn into a flower evil
整個植物會變成花惡的樣子
so they finally know
所以他們最後知道說
at this place
在這個地方
In fact, the role of the BC gene
事實上BC基因的作用
need to use
需要用
Involvement of the E gene
E基因的參與
So they thought it was a very important
所以他們就認為這是一個很重要的
For example, this is a normal flower in the Arab world
比如說這是阿拉伯界的正常的一個花
This is a mutation in the E gene
這個是E基因發生突變
you take it apart we say outside in
你把它拆開我們說從外而內
four flowers two
四個花二
four petals
四個花瓣
six stamens
六個熊蕊
The ratio of two fused hearts
兩個融合的心比
But you can find that it looks exactly like Hua Er
但是你可以發現它完全都是像花二的樣子
This looks a lot like a mutation in the BC gene
這個樣子就很像BC基因發生突變
so they know
所以他們就知道
The BC gene must be together with the E gene in the future
BC基因一定要跟E基因這個一起以後
they only use
他們才用
so you can see that it's not just a morphological change
所以你可以發現它不只是形態發生改變
When your gene is mutated
當你這個基因發生突變的時候
on our exterior
在我們的外表情
You see we're using an electron microscope
你看我們在用電子顯微鏡上
Look at the electron microscope
電子顯微鏡你看
In normal Wildtide
在正常的Wildtide
normal bead words
正常珠的話
Its flowers look like they have blowholes on them
它的花二看起來上面有氣孔
it's green
它是綠色的
You can find that it has pores for photosynthesis
你可以發現它有氣孔可以行光合作用
Its petal shape is like this
它的花瓣形狀是這樣
but when you
但是當你
When a gene is mutated
一基因發生突變的時候
you look like flower even in the petals
你甚至在花瓣的樣子都像是花二
So you're not only a waigan change
所以你不僅是外甘改變
You change even its very nature
你連它的本質你都發生了改變
So in the end people are now
所以說最後人家現在就是
There is a called ABCE Model
有一個叫做ABCE Model
For example, for the first one this time, you want to control the second petal of the flower
比如說這次第一個你要控制花二花瓣
You need the ABCE gene to make different combinations
就需要有ABCE這個基因去做不同的組合
I don't think there is any need to remember this.
我想這個裡面也不必去記的
But that is to say it has a
但是就是說它就是有一個
So is there something else involved?
所以是不是還有其他的東西參與呢
Yes
是的
Because there are still people in the land and land area who have discovered
因為現在陸陸區還有人發現
Others may have other proteins involved
其他可能有其他的蛋白質參與
for example
比如說
When your other gene is mutated
當你這個其他的基因發生突變以後
You know why it's called Superman
你知道為什麼叫做Superman
Because it has a lot of stamens
因為它有超級多的熊蕊
When your Superman gene mutates
當你這個Superman這個基因發生突變的時候
Its stamens will increase
它的熊蕊就會變多
Or if you look at this, it has
或者是說你看這個它有
it will have excessive flowering
它會有過多的花期
Like this one we just should have a normal flower with
像這個我們剛剛應該正常的花有
four petals
四個花瓣
You can find it this florescence this
你可以發現它這個花期這個
have changed
都改变了
even this doesn't look like a flower at all
甚至这个完全不像一朵花
So this is all made of these mutant beads
所以这个都是由这些突变珠
research we can
我们可以的研究
we accumulate
我们累积起来
we can slowly know
我们可以慢慢知道说
How do these genes get involved
这一些基因它怎么样去参与的
the whole flower
这个整个花的
Differentiation and development of flower buds
花芽的分化 发育
Even the formation of flower organs
甚至花的器官的形成
the role they play
他们所扮演的角色
In fact, there is quite a lot of space
其实是还有相当相当多的一个空间
For young students who are interested
给在座有兴趣的年轻学子
or other interested
或者是其他有兴趣的
and a big one
还有很大的一个
A space for research and development
一个研究发展的一个空间
The second one I will introduce to you
第二个我跟各位介绍一个
the so-called pollination of plants
就是所谓的植物的受粉作用
What we can talk about first is the so-called configuration body
我们可以先讲的是所谓的配置体
Formation of pollen exudation
花粉配出的形成
pollination
还有受粉作用
and the mechanism of pollen tube growth
还有花粉管生长的机制
this is a whole plant
这是一个整个植物
You can find from here to here
你可以发现从这个到这地方
the most important is
最重要的是
diploid on this side
在这一边都是二倍体
when you go through a deceleration split
当你经过一次减速分裂的时候
your so-called
你的这个所谓的
this is pollen
这个是花粉
will form pollen
会形成花粉
Pollen mother cells make pollen
花粉母细胞会形成花粉
pollen tube
最后产生花粉管
This is the last and this is the embryo
这是最后这个是胚
The central cell will form a
中央细胞会形成一个
so-called embryo sac
所谓的胚囊
There are three anti-bamboo cells inside
里面有三个反竹细胞
a central cell
一个中央细胞
an egg
一个卵
Next to it are two saprophytic cells
旁边还有两个腐细胞
this is the last
这是最后
it's a whole
这是一个整个
throughout the developmental process
整个发育的过程
how do you know this situation
怎么知道这个情况
because it's still the same
是因为还是一样
Tubian Bamboo
图便竹
so far
在目前为止
this is what we are talking about
这个是我们现在说的
In fact, you can see this in 2008
其实这个你看2008年
But over the past 10 years
但是在过去10年以来
more genes found
发现了更多更多的基因
But first with this
但是先以这个来讲
in the thoracic stamen
在胸蕊磁蕊
You can find that the most important thing is
你可以发现最重要就是
pollen mother cell
花粉母细胞
And this big embryo
还有这个大胚子
Mother cells they go through like this
母细胞他们经过这样
you can find
你可以发现
every gene
每一个基因
every process
每一个过程
Here is a genetic mutation
这边都是一个基因发生竹变
will affect this
就会影响到这个
so we accumulate
所以我们累积起来
We can know that
我们可以知道
all these genes
这所有的基因
in the middle of this whole process
在这整个过程中间
role involved
参与的角色
you don't have to remember
你不用去记
because i can't remember
因为我也记不得
But on these files
但是这些文件上
can be found
都查得到
but so later
但是所以以后
let's do some more research
我们再做研究
because we see what happens to this pollen at some stage
因為我們看到這個花粉在某個階段發生了什麼變化
We can go back to the literature and think
我們可以回文獻去想
It turned out that the gene was mutated
原來是那個基因發生突變
Is our gene a protein? Does it have any interaction with it?
我們的基因是不是蛋白質是不是跟它有什麼互相做相互作用關係
we can make progress
我們就可以進步的往下做
So this is some of our information in that place
所以這個都是一些我們的資訊在那個地方
whole pollination
整個受粉作用
The whole pollination basically the pollination of plants is
整個受粉作用基本上植物的受粉作用是
Pollen is an extremely dry condition
花粉是一個極度乾燥的一個情況
When the pollen is ripening it dehydrates
當花粉在成熟的時候它會脫水
it will have a dehydration
它會有一個脫水
so the pollen falls on the stigma
所以花粉會落在柱頭上
The pollen then absorbs water on the stigma
然後花粉會在柱頭上吸水
But this process has to go through a lot of so-called cell-to-cell interactions
但這個過程中間要經過非常多的一個所謂的細胞和細胞之間的交互作用
For example, in the plant kingdom, there is a thing called self-inferiority and credible
比如說在植物界有一個叫做自交不清可信
That is to say, your own pool core will repel
也就是說你自己的池蕊會排斥
or keep yourself from pollen with the same genotype
或者不讓你自己具有相同基因型的花粉身上
One may be absorbing water on the stigma
一個可能是在柱頭上吸水
self-ambiguity
那叫做包質體的自交不清核性
But if it's inside the style
但是如果是在花柱裡面
Let it grow to a certain stage
讓它長到某一個階段以後
Don't let it be long is ligand body
不讓它是長的是配質體的
self ambiguous
自交不清核性
I won't be there today
我今天不會再跟那裡
Because the mechanism is very, very complicated
因為那個機制非常非常的複雜
Finally the pollen hall will enter the style after the growth
最後花粉館會進入花柱生長以後
Finally two packets of information will be
最後會將兩個信息包
Send to distribution to complete double collection
送到配出完成雙重收金
Throughout this process you may have
這整個過程中間你可能有
There are bee plum blossoms or insect plum blossoms
有蜂梅花或者是蟲梅花
You can take the pollen with you
你可以把這些花粉帶過去
When the last pollen is on the stigma
最後花粉在柱頭上的時候
it will generate a
它會產生了一個
This is the epidermis of the stigma
這個是柱頭的表皮系
That epidermal cell that produces pollen tubes
那個表皮系包它會產生花粉館
Eventually the pollen hall will grow inside the style
最後花粉館會在花柱裡面生長
This is the practice style
這個是實行的花柱
you can look under a microscope
你可以去看在顯微鏡底下
You go dye a special thing called
你去染一個特別的東西叫做
dye
染劑
you can see
你可以看到
Every growth is a pollen hall
每一個生長的都是一個花粉館
These little bits are called Kalus Pluck
這些一點一點的叫做Kalus Pluck
It's the pollen hall that keeps growing
就是花粉館不斷的在生長的
in the middle
中間的時候
It keeps forming structures like this
它不斷的會形成這樣的構造
only let
只讓
The tip of the pollen is alive
最尖端的花粉是有活性的
That place brings two exquisite
那个地方带来两个精致
I once did an experiment
我曾经做过一个实验
After losing weight
就是瘦了粉以后
you put that stigma
你把那个柱头
And part of the pollen style is removed
还有一部分的花粉花柱去掉
as long as you keep the topmost pollen structure intact
只要你维持最尖端的花粉结构完整
it last it doesn't need
它最后它不需要
have used those pollen tubes or
已经用过那些花粉管或者
Thin Gold
它就自己可以完成瘦金
you turn it upside down
你把它倒过来
It can still grow slower
它还是可以长得比较慢
because of this kind of place
因为这种地方
But you can still lose gold
但是还是可以瘦金
so you know it's a very
所以你知道这是一个非常
Active means magnetic sharp
主动的就是说磁锐
will send a message
会送出一个讯息
Attracts pollen tubes to my kind
吸引花粉管我这种
This is a hollow style
这是空心的花柱
For example like we have
比如说像我们有
One of our experimental materials
我们的一个实验材料
Iron Cannon Lily
叫铁炮百合
You can spot these pollen tubes
你可以发现这些花粉管
grows along the inner epidermal cells
就沿着内部的表皮细胞生长
Pollen tubes are what we just talked about
花粉管就是我们刚刚讲的
this tip
这个尖端
what you see under the tip microscope
你在尖脂显微镜底下看到
The previous one is a
前面这个是一个
just very very
就是非常非常
seems to be a clean place
好像很干净的地方
seen under a microscope
在显微镜底下看到
It is a lot of different packages
它是有很多的异包
in this whole structure
在这整个结构
last this
最后这个
This pollen hall is constantly being formed
這個花粉館不斷地會有形成
The so-called Kelas Park
所謂的Kelas Park
take this pollen house
就把這個花粉館
So in the end you just need this place to finish
所以最後你只要這個地方完成
Take it today to put the last two gold cells
今天端它就可以把最後兩個金細胞
to that pool
送到那個池壘
Match pigs to complete double insemination
配豬完成雙重受精
So the last two gold cells
所以最後兩個金細胞
This pollen shop will deliver
這個花粉館會送到
This place is called the pig hole
叫做豬孔這個地方
complete fertilization
就完成受精
For example, this is one percent of our iron pack
比如說這是我們鐵包百分之一
You can find out if you look hard enough
你可以發現如果你眼睛夠看
This is a pig hole, this is an embryonic pig
這是豬孔這是胚豬
this is fat
這是脂肪
you can discover a pollen house
你可以發現一個花粉館
just go in from here
正好從這邊進去
So throughout the
所以在整個的
Speaking of the double fertilization of plants as a whole
整個來講植物的雙重受精的話
probably
大概就是
so a pollen house
所以一個花粉館
last middle gold
最後中間一個金子
Pollen hall is the bear plastosome
花粉館是熊配質體
Its purpose is to combine two gold cells
它的目的就是把兩個金細胞
sent to this embryo sac
送到這個胚囊
Embryo sac should be double fertilized
應該講胚囊完成雙重受精
one of them will follow
其中一個是會跟
egg is soft fertilization
egg就是軟受精
double fertilization
雙重受精
a sperm will follow it
一個精子會跟它
In addition, it will follow this polar cell
另外是會跟這個極細胞
cell center
Centro cell
The two poles in the central cell
中央細胞裡面的兩個極合
complete fertilization
完成受精
So how much is 1 plus 1 equal to an egg?
所以卵是1加1是等於多少
2 is 2n
2是2n
But in the end this central cell
但是最後這個中央細胞
What will this fertilized central cell form
這個受精的中央細胞會形成什麼
breastfeeding
佩乳
So the seed of the plant is very special
所以佩乳在植物的種子很特別
it belongs to 3n
它是屬於3n的
so it is triploid
所以它是3倍體
So this is a very special construct
所以這個是一個很特別的構造
And finally after this fertilized egg
然後最後在這個受精卵以後
It will eventually go through a series of fetal development
它最後再會再經過一系列的佩胎發育
will generate interval
會產生間隔
the last seed formed
最後形成的一個種子
The following is probably
下面這個大概就是
How to grow the high efficiency of this cartoon
這個卡通高出效大概是怎麼樣去種
a pollen tube
一個花粉管
Inside the pollen tube are two sperm cells
花粉管裡面有兩個精細胞
will go in along the bead hole
會有沿著珠孔進去
There should be a bead hole in it
應該要有珠孔進去
from one of the two so-called saprophytic cells
會從兩個所謂的腐細胞中間的一個
destroyed
破壞掉
So in the end one of the sperm cells
所以最後其中一個精細胞
will follow this soft cell
會跟這個軟細胞
complete fertilization
完成受精
form what is called a Zygote
形成所謂的一個Zygote
is to receive nuclei
就是接核子
This is rotten cell
這個是腐細胞
Rot cells, this is pink cells
腐細胞這個是粉細胞
So one of them will follow it
所以其中一個會跟它
Also this is a central cell that has a collection
另外這是一個中央細胞有一個集合
The central cell communicates with it
中央細胞會跟它傳
So far, probably the above three are called antipodal cells
目前為止大概上面三個叫做反足細胞
as far as I know
就我所知
now it must be working
現在它一定是有作用的
Just like everyone has a length
就像人人不是有茫長嗎
People think that Mangchang is nothing
人家覺得茫長沒有什麼
but found
但是發現
May now find out that Mang Chang actually
可能現在發現茫長其實
In fact, it has some functions
其實還有它的一些作用
I don't know what it does
是什麼作用其實我也不知道
It's just that people say it's useful
只是人家說有用
So I guess the three antipodal cells
所以我想這三個反足細胞
It's not clear what effect
有什麼作用並不是很清楚
So it's probably over
所以大概最後就完了
Finally this will form the so-called Peyru
最後這個就會形成所謂的Peyru
This will form the so-called Pey
這個就會形成所謂的Pey
This is a photo of the whole
這是一個這整個的過照
Gum plant
植膠植物的
plant glue
植物的植膠
We just talked about the ones with stone cores
我們剛剛講過有石芯的
For example, like our so-called Arab world
比如說像我們所謂的阿拉伯界
or hollow
或者是空芯的
This is Iron Cannon Baihe
這是鐵砲白河
You can find this is them these pollen houses will go along this
你可以發現這是他們這些花粉館會沿著這個走
So in the middle of the pollination process?
所以在整個受粉過程中間呢
From the whole stigma pollen falling on the stigma to being completely fat
從整個柱頭花粉落在柱頭到受到脂肪完
Embryo pigs look throughout and find that there are two pollen halls in the middle of the process
胚豬整個你看發現花粉館在這個過程中間有兩個
Two shop terms means one
兩個shop term 就是要一個
it's like we're going home today
就很像我們今天回家
you are now on freeway
你現在上freeway
When you get to the freeway, you see
上到freeway的時候你看到
i live in taoyuan
我住在桃園
I saw Taoyuan
我看到桃園了
I'm leaving home
我就要出家流道口
right
對不對
out of the house
出了家流道口
you want to go back to your car park
你要回到你家定車場
do you still have a term
你是不是還有一個term
so it's like finally he's going home
所以就像最後他要回到家
So he has two shop terms
所以他有兩個shop term
These two are very, very important
他這兩個就是非常非常重要的
And now scientists are researching that
然後現在科學家研究說
in the middle of this whole process
在這整個過程中間
A shop term is called funical
一個shop term就叫做funical
It's a guiding for pig pie
就是豬餅的一個guiding
pollen hall
花粉館
it has to sense
它必須要sense到
message from the gametophyte
持配子體送出來的訊息
Told you that you were coming out of here
告訴你說你要從這裡出來了
i'm here he's going in
我在這裡他要進去
The other one is from Zhukou
另外一個是從珠口
he will
他也會
So only two attract
所以只有兩個吸引
for example
比如說
when you plant
當你這個植物
Under normal conditions of this pollen
在這個花粉的正常的情況底下
Every
每一個
AmbroSecPanel
AmbroSecPanel
Will only accept one pollen tube
只會接受一個花粉管
so there will only be one pollen tube
所以只會有一根花粉管
along the bead handle
沿著這個珠柄的位置
will enter the micropyle to complete the double release
會進到珠孔完成雙重受解
When you plant this it doesn't matter
當你植物這個沒有所謂的
when holding the gametophyte
持配子體的時候
it's basically
它基本上
Pollen will not recognize Signal
花粉不會認識到Signal
But other times when some plants mutate
但是其他有一些植物發生突變的時候
For example called Marmut
比如說叫做Marmut
when you do this it can
當你這個它可以
along the micropyle
沿著珠孔
To go along this Funicle is the bead handle
要沿著這個Funicle就是珠柄
it can pollen tubes know where to come out
它可以花粉管知道這裡出來
but it can't find a home
但是它找不到家
When this gene is mutated
當這個基因發生突變的時候
You can find all the pollen tubes
你可以發現所有的花粉管
can only go around outside
都只能在外面繞
It can't find the micropyle of McPad
它找不到麥克帕這個珠孔
so you know the gene
所以你知道這個基因
When a mutation occurs, there are two
發生突變的時候有兩個
First
第一個
when your gene is mutated
當你基因發生突變的時候
Your pollen tube can't help
你花粉管沒有辦法
sense to this from Chirui
sense到從池瑞這個
Embryo sac kidney out information
胚囊腎出來的信息
the second
第二個
Each of our original bead handles
我們原先每一個珠柄
only one pollen tube
只會有一個花粉管
You can find quite a few pollen tubes
你可以發現有相當多的花粉管
so you know the role it's involved in
所以你知道它參與的角色
The messaging is in this section
在訊息傳導是在這個部分
In addition there is this mute
另外有一個這個mute
you can spot pollen tubes
你可以發現花粉管
Yes, the normal pollen tubes I just talked about
對 我剛剛講的正常的花粉管
Go in from McPa
進去從麥克帕這個地方
After this beadhole goes in
這個珠孔進去以後
pollen tubes will burst
花粉管會爆掉
Exploding will release two gold pieces
爆掉會把兩個金子放出來
but this you can find
但是這個你可以發現
When your gene mutates
當你這個基因發生突變
Pollen tubes can go in along the stalk
花粉管可以沿著珠柄進去
Micropyretes can also be found
也可以找到珠孔
But it won't explode after it goes in
但是它進去以後它不會爆掉
so you can know
所以你可以知道
The role of this gene
這個基因參與的角色
Eventually the pollen tube will burst
最後花粉管要破掉
Release the two economic packages
把兩個經濟包釋放出來
So in this process there is quite a lot of
所以在這個過程就是有相當相當多的
a study of
的一個研究
Only then can we know how the entire pollen tube is frightened
我們才可以知道整個花粉管受驚的過程
So now we're going to just ask
所以我們現在我們就要只想要問
scientists are never satisfied
科學家永遠不滿足
these molecules
這些分子啊
pool core
池蕊
Or these pool configuration bodies sent out by it
或者是這些池配置體它送出來的
how did it come out
它怎麼送出來的
where did it come from
它從哪裡送出來的
So there is a scientist who just use the tight
所以呢有一個科學家他們就是用下緊
material of this plant
這個植物的材料
What's so special about this plant material?
這個下緊有什麼特別的一個植物材料
it has a bare
它有一個裸露的
embrane
embrane
the scientist
這個科學家
He's a pretty good guy
他是一個做的相當好的
Their article was published in Science
他們文章發表在Science
what's so special about this plant
它這個植物有什麼特別呢
That is to say, it matches
就是說它這個配
We used to pack this bag in it.
這個配囊我們以前都是包在裡面
but this one it's all exposed
但這個呢它都是裸露出來的
After you separate the accessory sac
當你把這個這個配囊分離出來以後呢
put it on your garnish
放在你的配上
You put it in the pollen hall
上面你放進花粉館
you can find
你可以發現
This is the so-called Mike Pie
這個就是所謂的麥克派
It's pig's mouth
就是豬口
you can find
你可以發現
This is the pollen hall that grows outside the body
這就在體外面生長的花粉館
will naturally run in
會自然而然地跑進去
complete fertilization
完成受精
you can find
你可以發現
Enter through the middle of the two rotting spiders
從兩個腐蜘褦中間的一個進去
it completes fertilization
它完成受精
They found a system like this
他們就發現有這樣子的一個系統
so he wants
所以他想
This is a very good system
這個是一個很不錯的系統
at least we know
我們最起碼我們知道
embryo sac
整個齒睿的胚囊
There are two rot lizards inside
裡面有兩個腐蜥褦
a central cell
一個中央細胞
one more egg
還有一個卵
And the above three anti-bamboo cells
還有上面三個反竹細胞
three anti-bamboo cells
三個反竹細胞
maybe too far
可能太遠了
they got here
他們有在這裡弄
At least we just look at the following
最起碼我們只是看下面這幾個
I went in with the pollen house
跟花粉館進去的
The carrion is more important
是腐蜥褦比較重要
eggs are more important
卵比較重要
or the central cell is more important
還是中央細胞比較重要
So they made a
所以他們就做了一個
very interesting experiment
非常有趣的一個實驗
controlled by laser
用雷射操控的
look
你看
They can use a combination of laser and microscope
他們可以用結合雷射和顯微鏡
It can be destroyed with great precision
它可以非常精準的破壞掉
One of the
其中一個
i can destroy
我可以破壞掉
Between the two rot packs
這兩個腐蜥包中間
Destroy this Centro cell
把這個Centro cell破壞掉
or two rotten cells
或者是兩個腐細胞
You destroy it with one hit of the laser
你用雷射一打就把它破壞掉
So you use various permutations
所以你用各種不同的排列組合
Destroys the morphology of various cells
破壞各種不同的細胞的形態
You can make a result like this
你可以做出這樣的結果
i can destroy a cell
我可以破壞一個細胞
destroy two cells
破壞兩個細胞
destroy three cells
破壞三個細胞
various combinations
各種不同的combination
We look at it for the whole ability to attract pollen tubes
我們看它對於整個吸引花粉管能力
Will it be affected
會不會受到影響
So in the end they found
所以最後它們發現
a fun one is
一個很好玩的一個就是
when you find out
當你發現
You just need a rotten cell
你只要有一個腐細胞
Next to it are the two cells next to the soft
旁邊就是那個軟旁邊的那兩個細胞
As long as one rotten cell is broken
只要有一個腐細胞壞掉
It's basically the ability to attract pollen tubes in
它基本上吸引花粉管進去的能力
just lower
就降低
Once you help put these two rotten cells
一旦你幫把這個兩個腐細胞
when completely destroyed
完全破壞掉的時候
Pollen tubes do not enter
花粉管過門不入
so what do they know
所以它們知道什麼
This signal is sent from two rotting cells
這個訊號是從兩個腐細胞送出來的
you also know never enough
你也知道永遠不會滿足
directly after ten years
就直接經過十年以後
they want to know what molecule
它們想要知道是什麼分子
So after 10 years they found
所以在10年以后他们就发现
ok let's see
好 我们来看看
In this case I put this
就既然这样 我就把这个
They can since they are naked
他们可以既然是裸露出来的
This ambrosex this matching capsule
这个ambrosex这个配囊
We'll just separate all the cells out of it
我们就把它所有的细胞都分离出来
cells in which we can
细胞其中我们可以
All it can find is the synergy cell
它可以找到的就是synergy cell
put this synergy cell
把这个synergy cell
go inside it protein law
它里面去做蛋白质定律
found a group of proteins
发现有一群蛋白质
This group of proteins is abundantly expressed
这群蛋白质大量的表现
Then it finds the gene
然后它就把这个基因找出来
then antibodies
然后产生了抗体
It can be found that it is really
可以发现它真的是在
ambrosex in the pig hole
ambrosex在猪孔那个地方
Then they did a cool
然后他们就做了一个很酷的
Is that the molecule
那是不是这个分子
Really attracts pollen tubes to grow
真的会吸引花粉管生长
really
还真的是
when you are cultivating people
你在培养民的时候
you found click here
你发现在这边点一下
you can find the pollen tube
你就可以发现花粉管
will reduce the growth in this place
会减在这个地方生长
So they found this
所以他们就发现了这个叫
defending like this protein
defensing like这个蛋白质
is involved in this thing
是参与这个东西
you can watch this grow
你可以看这个生长
you can watch this cool
你可以看这个很酷
It turns when it taps the pollen tube
它这边点一下花粉管就转弯
click it here again
它这边再点一下
pollen tube turns
花粉管就會轉彎
so you know something like this
所以你知道這樣的物
it attracts pollen tubes
它可以吸引花粉管的
That is, guide the growth of pollen tubes
就是說引導花粉管的生長
so this is a very interesting
所以這是一個非常有趣的
so in this
所以在這個
This is under this tight this plant material
這是在這個下緊這個植物材料
they just
他們就
we just found this
我們剛剛發現這個
Is there any other molecular wild material?
那是不是還有其他的分子野材
Recently they also found
最近他們也發現
Arab world has similar
阿拉伯界也有類似
but these
但是這些
In fact, what I want to tell you is a
其實我要跟各位講的是一個
Just now that is a dicotyledonous plant
剛剛那個是雙子葉植物
our monocots
我們單子葉植物
Iron Lily
鐵砲百合
iron lily this is a
鐵砲百合這是一個
it has a hollow style
它有一個中空的花柱
Then what
然後呢
We did an experiment
我們當時就做了一個實驗
we just want to say
我們就想說
We hollow these styles
我們把中空這些花柱
Since we want to attract pollen tubes to grow
既然要吸引花粉管生長
It should be these things in the style
應該這些在花柱裡面的東西
should play an important role
應該是扮演很重要的角色
and we wanted to say
而且我們那時候想說
Pollen tubes grow a bit like animal cells
花粉管生長有點像是動物細胞
especially in this
尤其在這個
so-called hollow pool
所謂的中空的池
The hollow style
中空的那個花柱
it is an attachment
它是一個附著
then grow on the move
然後在移動的生長
you just saw
你們剛剛看到
So we developed a way like this
所以我們就developed出這樣子一個方式
We really found you this is Nitroceus Memes
我們真的發現你這是Nitroceus Memes
This is an artificial membrane
這是一個人工的膜
When you coat this layer on the film
當你這膜上面coating了這一層
When this star exits you take the pollen tube
這Star Exit的時候你把花粉管
put the film on
膜放上去
You can find that the pollen tube seems to be
你可以發現這花粉管好像是
It's like a big foot extended like this
好像是一個大腳在上面這樣延伸
And finally we want to say
然後最後我們就想說
Indicates the substance inside
表示這個裡面這個物質
Possibly attached to pollen
可能是有跟花粉的附著
and attract growth
還有吸引生長
So after I graduated
所以後來我畢了業以後
The teachers in my doctoral class will continue to have a Post-up
我博士班的老師他們就繼續有一個Post-up
he will remember
他就記住下去
From this, they use lust analysis
他們就從這個用色神分析法
A substance is separated from it
裡面分出來一個物質
You can find that when this substance
你可以發現當這個物質
what he did was very
他做的那個很
That girl's eyes are really amazing
那個女生眼睛真的是超厲害
he's on this slope
他在這個在坡片上面
Then dig a hole in the middle of this thing
然後把這個東西中間挖一個洞
you put that thing you can put in
你把那個東西你可以放進
you are variously purified
你各種不同purified
Different Purified Things
不同純化的東西
Then you take the pollen grains
然後你把花粉粒
The benefits of Iron Cannon Lily are
鐵砲擺合的好處是
Its pollen grains are super large
它的花粉粒超級大
it's super big
它超級大
you can see it with meat
你用肉也可以看得到
Then it circles around the outside
然後它就圍在外面一圈
so that the pollen tube germination is all facing outward
讓花粉管的萌發都朝外
pick slowly with a needle
用針去慢慢挑
If today this material
如果說今天這個物質
can attract pollen tubes
可以吸引花粉管身上
It will grow outward and grow in again
它就會往外長 又會長進來
if it is water
如果是水的話
it will grow wildly
它就會亂長
So later it found
所以後來它發現
really this thing
真的這個東西
it affects it
它會影響到它
and it's a protein
而且它是個蛋白質
When you, the stored substance
當你這個存化出來的物質
after you add
你加了以後
lost activity
就失去的活性
Finally they found a
最後他們發現一個叫做
Cymocyanin
Cymocyanin
it's a protein
這是一個蛋白質
So that means
所以就是說
possibly among different species
可能在不同的物種中間
have different molecules
有不同的分子
or protein
或者是蛋白質
participate in this mechanism
參與在這個機制上
So I think this is a
所以我想這個就是一個
That means we're in the middle of the process
就是說我們在這個過程中間
Now of course one after another
現在當然陸陸續續
students now
現在各個學生
their laboratory
他們實驗室
they talk
他們講說
ok we now know
好 我們現在知道
There is a general definition of Micropile
有Micropile的概定
What is the general definition of Funical?
那Funical的概定是什麼
the other pollen tube
那另外一個花粉管
to go all the way down from the casting head
要從鑄頭一直往下走
What is this long-distance signal?
這個長距離的訊號又是什麼
So scientists are never satisfied
所以科學家永遠不滿足
So they also try to
所以他們也盡量在
I heard that I found it
在聽說是找到了
but not yet published
但是還沒有發表
We'd like to say that we'll probably know soon
我們想說大概最近很快就會知道說
What molecules are attracted to this petal jar?
到底是什麼分子會吸引這個花瓣罐
All the way from the casting head along the style
一路從鑄頭沿著花柱
finally to the fat
最後到脂肪
Embryo pig
胚豬
its growth
它的生長
so it's a process
所以這是一個過程
The next thing I want to tell you is that we have been here for about ten years
接下來我要跟各位講的就是我們在過去這大概十幾年了
Twenty or ten years
二十年十幾年了
Ten years?
十幾年嗎
should be about the same
應該對差不多
I do Post-Auto there
我在那做Post-Auto
about ten years
大概十幾年
I'm sorry for twenty years
對不起二十幾年
some recent tools
最近的一些工具
For example, we have long believed that
比如說我們現在長久以來認為說
You want to see the finer structure of the cell
你要看到細胞更細微的構造
You're going to the electron microscope
你要走到電子顯微鏡
electron microscope
電子顯微鏡
right
對不對
The light microscope has its one limit
光學顯微鏡有它的一個極限
but in the past this
但是在過去這
In addition to a research and development of optical microscopes in recent years
這幾年除了光學顯微鏡的一個研發
There is also the root of a technology called the digital camera
還有一個所謂的數位相機的技術的根
We have something called a confocal optical microscope
我們有一個叫做共惡交光學顯微鏡
This makes the optical microscope
這個讓光學顯微鏡
FusionExcel's optical microscope seems to be reborn again
富裕的光學顯微鏡好像又有一個御火重生
an opportunity for regeneration
再生的一個契機
The other one is that we now have really good computers
另外一個就是我們現在有非常棒的電腦
works fast enough
速度運作夠快
It is possible to process these images
可以做這些影像的處理
Then there are some fluorescent proteins
然後另外有一些螢光的蛋白質
Production of fluorescent substances
螢光的物質的產生
Finally there is a laser system
最後有一個雷射的系統
These three
這三個
These four things finally make a
這四個東西最後造就了一個
We now have what's called a confocal microscope
我們現在有所謂的叫共惡交顯微鏡
Many research institutes now have
現在很多的研究單位都有
What is the so-called confocal microscope
所謂的叫共惡交顯微鏡是什麼
Our Traditional Fluorescence Microscope
我們傳統的螢光顯微鏡
its light source
它的光源
The message we received was like this
我們所收到的訊息是這樣子一整片
but conjugate focus
但是共惡交
It can be said that it can use a computer to see
可以就是說它可以利用電腦去看
so you can put your laser
所以你可以把你的雷射
only on a certain layer
只打在某一層的
it's yours it's yours
就是你的這是你的
This is your specimen of your plant
這是你的植物的你的標本
You can only position in this collar
你只可以你可以定位在這個領
or locate here
或定位這裡
you put other noise signals
你把其他雜訊的訊號
Use Filter to filter it out
利用Filter把它過濾掉
So what effect does it have
所以它有什麼樣的效果
This is the tradition we see
這個是傳統我們所看到的
Conventional Fluorescence Microscopy
傳統的螢光顯微鏡
but you can see
但是你可以看到
concord microscope
共和交顯微鏡
Can make your image see more clearly
可以讓你的影像看得更清楚
Your image can be seen more clearly
你的影像可以看得更清楚
For example, we can in this
比如說我們可以在這個
You can see us using
你可以看到我們利用
It can be at different delivery locations
它可以在不同的定交的位置
We can scan a pollen tube
我們可以掃描一顆花粉管
top to bottom
從上到下
you can go from top to bottom
你可以從上到下
Finally, you can use the computer to combine
最後你可以用電腦組合出
a 3D construct
一個3D的構造
for example
比如說
This is an air port that our lab is working on
這是我們實驗室正在做的一個氣口
it's arabian
這是阿拉伯界的
arabian world you can find
阿拉伯界你可以發現
Scanning TV mirrors seem to look like
掃描式電視鏡好像看起來
Give you cool 3D
給你蠻酷的3D的
A bit of a 3D effect, right?
有點3D立體的效果對不對
This we also see the fluorescent representative
這個我們也看到螢光代表
How can the effect of generating electricity
怎麼可以發電的效果
but
但是呢
You use
你用
Very focal effect
很focal的效果
what effect can you give
你可以給你什麼樣的效果
you can see
你可以看得到
you can scan
你可以掃描
you can swipe from top to bottom
你可以從上掃到下
You can see that this is a stomata structure
你可以發現這是一個氣孔的構造
You can make the pores have a three-dimensional structure like this
你可以讓氣孔有這樣子的一個立體的構造
This is from top to bottom
這是從上掃到下
It's okay if you're not satisfied
你不滿足沒問題
we can go from left to right
我們可以從左到右
you can see this blowhole
你可以看到這個氣孔
These are two air pockets
這是兩個氣孔氣包
Then there is a hole in the middle
然後中間這是一個孔
where the gas can freely pass through
就可以氣體可以自由通透的地方
you can side
你可以從側面
A microscope made like this from the side
側面去做這樣子的一個顯微鏡
So this can be used quite a bit
所以這個可以用得相當多
It's okay if you don't think it's enough
如果你覺得這還不過癮沒關係
We can do 3D
我們可以做3D的
You can use different
你可以利用配合不同的
You can make structures in 3D
你可以做出3D的構造
So you can combine it with
所以你可以用結合
you can scan different
你可以掃描不同的
You combine all the images of this thing
你把這個東西影像全部結合起來
you can watch
你可以看
so you can see
所以你可以看得到
If your protein special Label is in a certain pair
如果說你的蛋白質特別Label在某一個對子
You can see your protein in
你可以看得到你這個蛋白質在
this cell
这个细胞
or a particular location inside the cell
或这个细胞里面的某一个特别的位置
So you can push the function to heat it
所以你可以推热它的功能
So this is a pretty interesting
所以这个是一个相当有趣的
conventional microscope
传统的显微镜
We can see that
我们可以看到
or by silver cursor
或用银光标定的方式
or elevator microscope
或电梯显微镜
you can tell
你可以看得出来
This seems to look fine detail
这好像看起来细节不错
but what
但是什么
They are all dead cells
它们全都是死的细胞
they are all
它们全部都是
you will want to say
你会想说
So what would it be like under the living body?
那在活体之下它会是怎么样呢
So by one like this
所以由这样子的一个
So finally one of the things we found was
所以最后我们有发现的一个就是
silver light protein
银光蛋白
i think everyone knows
我想大家都知道
We have a lot of news from before the network
我们从网络之前有很多新闻
silver light fish zebrafish
银光鱼 斑马鱼
all kinds
各式各样
It is mainly a silver light protein
主要就是一个这个银光蛋白质
I used to find green
以前是发现绿色
red now
现在有红色
various colors
各式各样的颜色
when your color
当你这个颜色
When you are the appearance of silver light protein
当你这是银光蛋白质的出现的时候
you can find
你可以发现
assortment you can use on animals
各式各样你可以用在动物
can be used on plants
可以用在植物
how it is used in plants
它如何用在植物
For example, we can use the protein
比如说我们可以用在蛋白质
Although we see stomata
虽然我们看到气孔
ovules you see
你看到的胚珠
This is the whole embryo
这是整个胚
This is the middle of the process of cell division we see
这个是我们看到的细胞分裂的过程中间
A variation of imitation hammer wire
仿锤丝的一个变化
or inside a plant leaf that we can get
或者是在一个我们可以从植物的叶片里面
do so-called Potoplas
做所谓的Potoplas
Then we can do some analysis
然后我们可以做一些分析
Ours is, for example, this is
我们这个是比如说这个是
This is the chloroplast
这个是叶绿体
we can do many many things
我们可以做很多很多的东西
others you can see
其他的你可以看到
like a cytoskeleton
像细胞骨架
Cytoskeleton Sidere Scalata
细胞骨架Sidere Scalata
You can find this is
你可以发现这是
This is the fresh hair on the surface of the leaf
这个是叶表面的鲜毛
you can see these cytoskeletons
你可以看到这些细胞骨架
how do you form such a construct
你如何形成这样一个构造
the one we just talked about
我们刚刚讲的一个
Can see Live Image
可以看到Live Image
This is a Live Image
这是一个Live Image
You can see that its Label is imitation hammer wire
你可以看到它Label的是仿锤丝
Microtubule
Microtubule
you can find
你可以发现
you see the cells are dividing
你看到细胞正在分裂
you can see
你可以看到
right in front of your eyes
就在你眼前
you can see living cells
你可以看得到活体的细胞
Live Whole Your Gene Bomber
活体的整个你的基因弹牌子
the whole change
整个的变化
Although I think it's a
虽然我想这是一个
for us is a
对我们来讲是一个
very useful tool
非常有用的一个工具
Is it useful?
对不对 有用的
So we are now saying
所以说我们现在就是说
Both these tools
既有用这些工具
what we couldn't do before
我們以前不能做的
For example, before we could only say
比如說我們以前只能說
whip out a protein or something
抽出一個蛋白質或什麼
Now you can use fluorescent subtraction to mirror
現在你可以利用螢光減為鏡
we use some way to turn straight
我們用一些轉直的方式
We can see these cells in living
我們可以看到活體這些細胞
even you can see the little cytoplasm
甚至你就可以看到小小的細胞質
Inside the Cytoskeleton of Matter Research
物質研的細胞骨架裡面
running in and out
跑來跑去
wait till we have one
等一下我們才會有一個
A video to introduce to you
一個影像跟大家介紹
Then our laboratory research is mainly
那我們實驗室研究主要是
Some genes involved in the sexual biomass of plants
參與在植物的有性生質的一些基因
Same
一樣
This is the life of the whole plant
這是整個植物的生活
Our main thing is
我們主要的是
The earliest our laboratory
最早我們實驗室
I'm personally interested in pollen
我個人有興趣的是花粉
Because I think pollen is really a
因為我覺得花粉實在是一個
very cool
非常酷的
Why
為什麼
it is a cell
它是一個細胞
it has its own cell box
它有自己的細胞盒
we call nutrition box
我們叫做營養盒
But inside this cell
但是這個細胞裡面
two more gold cells
又有兩個金細胞
So it is an extremely degenerate
所以它是一個極度退化的
a bear configuration
一個熊配置體
but it's a cell box
但是它是一個細胞盒
so it can be done
所以它是可以做
Pretty good for a cytology
相當好的做一個細胞學
study one
研究的一個
Then in the past and later, in the past few years in the future, we will slowly expand
然後在過去後來我們在未來過去這幾年我們就要慢慢拓廣
We found that some of the research we did started to lead to the so-called configuration
我們發現了我們做的一些研究開始牽著到所謂的配置
The development of the male and female gametes
那個雄配 雌配尺體的發育
In the end, we also found that something to do with the seeds
最後我們也發現跟種子有關
So we all revolve around the reproductive growth of so-called plants
所以我們都是圍繞在所謂的植物的生殖生長
For the past few years we have used
我們在過去這幾年我們用的
We want to be able to study certain genes or proteins
我們就希望能夠研究某一些基因或者蛋白質
How to participate in so-called male gametes or pollination
如何參與所謂的雄配尺體或者受粉
or the process of so-called embryonic development
或者是所謂的胚胎發育的過程
We used iron cannon lily rice and Arabian circles as materials
我們用了鐵砲百合水稻還有阿拉伯界當作材料
But let me introduce to you today
但是我今天先各位介紹一下
We have spent the past few years in Iron Cannon Lily
我們在過去這幾年我們在鐵砲百合
Iron Lily
鐵砲百合
Why did we use Iron Cannon Lily in the first place?
我們當初為什麼要用鐵砲百合
You go and see
你去看看
This is the anther of the iron cannon lily
這是鐵砲百合的花藥
The small and pitiful one next to it is the flower of the Arabian world
旁邊那小小很可憐是阿拉伯界的花
You can find that its anthers are much larger than other people's flowers
你可以發現它的花藥都比人家的花大很多
It's certainly a good material
它當然是一個很好的材料
Another one you can find
另外一個你可以發現
it is a hollow style
它是一個中空的花柱
There are ways to collect so-called
有辦法收集所謂的
Pollen House at Invival
在Invival的花粉館
The third we found
第三個我們發現
its stigma
它的柱頭
it constantly secretes a
它會不斷地分泌一種
sticky sticky stuff
很黏很黏的東西
Our name is Stella Exde
我們叫做Stella Exde
You can find this sticky down
你可以發現這個黏低下來的
we can collect this
我們可以收集這個
we can find out
我們可以發現
Later this Stella Exde is very magical
後來這Stella Exde非常的神奇
it has something in it
它裡面有某一個東西
When your pollen is placed at minus 20 degrees
當你的花粉放在負20度
saved for 6 months
存了6個月
Then you stop normally and take it out
然後你正常停完拿出來的話
The efficiency of the pollen hall is very poor
花粉館蒙發效率非常的差
right? think about it
對不對 你想想看
Don't talk about people
不要說人啊
Pollen House, right?
花粉館對不對
like a cell
像一個細胞
pollen grain
花粉粒
But pollen like you
但是你這樣子的花粉
stored pollen
儲存過花粉
You add Stella Exde
你加進去Stella Exde
About 10% Stella Exde
大概10%的Stella Exde
It restores the germination of pollen tubes
它可以恢復花粉館的蒙發
So it's kind of like a rejuvenation effect
所以有點像回春的效果
so our laboratory
所以我們實驗室
interested in this too
對這個也滿有興趣的
We Later We Now Lab
我們後來我們現在實驗室
We draw this Stella Exde
我們抽集這Stella Exde
We want to be able to Purify its molecule
我們希望能夠Purify它的molecule
So we use the so-called
所以我們利用所謂的
Chromatic Analysis
色成分析法
We have divided into different Fraction
我們分出了不同的Fraction
And one of the ones we found now
然後我們現在找到的其中有一個
These two freshers very much retain such activity
這兩個freshers非常保有這樣的活性
And the molecules are now probably identified as well.
然後分子也現在也大概鑒定出來了
just don't know what it is
只是還不知道它到底是
Its three-dimensional 3D structure is left-handed and right-handed
它的立體3D的結構到底是左旋右旋
Or does this molecule have other derivatives?
或者是說這個分子是不是還有其他的衍生物
We look a bit like a derivative of ancetonic acid
我們看起來有點像是一個安西酸的衍生物
But now we have to go further
但是我們現在還要進一步的
Hope to be able to synthesize to test
希望能夠合成去測試
so this is where we are
所以這是我們在這邊
Because the pollen house I just talked about
因為我剛剛講的花粉館
You see, the pollen hall can be used as
你看花粉館可以作為
basically what happens inside a cell
基本上在一個細胞裡面所發生的
So the message goes
所以訊息傳導了
Cap ion goes in
蓋離子進去了
All of these are on the pollen pavilion
所有這些在花粉館上面通通都有
so it is a very good as a material
所以它是一個非常好的作為一個材料
So let's say we have two graduate students
所以比如說我們有兩個研究生
high school student
高中生
high school students they will one day
高中生他們有一天就
They come to our laboratory
四大附中的他們就來我們實驗室
He said he wanted to do a science exhibition, and I said yes.
說想要做科展我說好啊
what do you want to do
那你就想要做什麼
I want to say this is good for them to do
我想說這個不錯給他們去做
you can find them found to do
你可以發現他們發現做到
Finally, it was found that when the pollen tubes are in the middle of the process
最後發現當花粉管蒙發的過程中間的時候
What happens to the oil in it
它裡面的油體會發生的變化
changes in oil
油體會發生的變化
Later in fact we were before
後來事實上我們就在以前
A few years ago we discovered that in plants
前幾年我們發現在植物
We can use Iron Cannon Lily
我們就可以用鐵砲百合
Although it is an iron cannon lily, although it cannot be genetically modified
它雖然鐵砲百合雖然不能做基因轉值
But scientists are still very powerful
但是科學家還是很厲害用什麼
gene gun
用基因槍
We take the proteins we find
我們把我們找出來的蛋白質
Then we code on an energy
然後我們coding在一個精力上面
like say this is us
像比如說這是我們
Not sorry
不對不起
plasticizing
plastamine
a plastid
一個質體
have the genes we want
有我們要的基因
Then we use the gene gun
然後我們用基因槍
Hit this gene until after this
把這個基因打到這個以後
Let's use comfoca to see
我們再用comfoca去看
so you can find
所以你可以發現
iron lily
這在鐵砲百合
you can find
你可以發現
This protein can really express
這個蛋白質真的是可以表現
Then we have this one on the oil body
然後我們這是一個在油體上
Purified protein
所purify下來的蛋白質
you can find
你可以發現
As the pollen tube grows
隨著花粉管的生長
You can find these oil bodies
你可以發現這些油體
really works constantly
真的不斷的在運作
so we know real pollen tubes
所以我們知道真的花粉管
at least we
至少我們
Later experiments also found
後來的實驗也發現
When the whole pollen hall is covered
在整個花粉館蒙發的時候
There is a group of fats that change
有一群的脂肪會改變
Another group of fat will increase
另外有一群的脂肪會增加
May be involved in cell membrane growth
可能參與了細胞膜生長
Because the pollen hall grows it needs the cell membrane
因為花粉館生長它需要細胞膜
Constant supply of cell membrane
不斷的提供細胞膜
those material
那些物質上
So that might be the mechanism
所以那個可能是那個機制
So we're in the middle of the process
所以我們在這個過程中間
we also found a
我們也找到了一個
a so-called cytoskeletal protein
一個就是所謂的細胞骨架蛋白
It's called LIM
它叫做LIM
Then we also did some experiments
然後我們也做了一些的實驗
What are cytoskeletal proteins?
什麼叫細胞骨架蛋白呢
it's a cartoon
這是一個卡通
you can find
你可以發現
this is the root of a plant
這是一個植物的根
Then they made genetically modified plants
然後他們做了轉基因植物
He found that this protein only had GFG fluorescence
他發現這個蛋白只有了GFG螢光
You can find it manifesting in root hairs
你可以發現它在根毛表現
You see and then they order
你看然後他們這單
it's all real
這邊都是真的
The words below the back are cartoons
在後面下面的話就是卡通
that's what they found
就是他們發現
This is a cytoskeletal protein
這是一個細胞骨架蛋白
It should help you out of the so-called
它應該是會幫你出所謂的
Acting Weiss's A Knot
Acting維斯的一個結
What is the structure of these micro divisions that you finally found out
這些微師結構你最後發現它是什麼
it's...you can find it walking around
它是...你可以發現它在走來走去
It's these proteins it's an acid binding protein
它這些蛋白質它是一個acid binding protein
it has a nonspecies species on it
它上面有一個非種的物種
You can find it can walk up and down on this
你可以發現它可以引在這上面走來走去
So it's fun. This is the Western Gaogu religion.
所以很好玩 這就是西部高古教
This is Sytle skeleton
這就是Sytle skeleton
The thing we make doesn't go like this
我們做的那個東西不是這樣走
but also something like
但是也有一點像
So for example we find
所以比如說我們發現
when normal in this pollen house
當正常在這個花粉館
We still use the gene gun to express
我們還是用基因槍去表現
You can find our protein
你可以發現我們的蛋白質
it will follow the cytoskeleton
它會跟這個細胞骨架
It's F acting, it's the combination of micro-teachers
就是F acting 就是微師做結合
But when you're dealing with this micro division's decomposing matter
但是當你處理這個微師的分解物質的時候
You can find that the combination is gone
你可以發現這個結合就不見了
Then when we do a lot of this performance
然後當我們大量在這個表現的時候
you see it found
你看它發現
When pollen tubes are abundant
花粉管大量表现的时候
Originally normal growth pollen tube
原先正常生长的花粉管
You will find that there is a middle pollen tube
会发现有一个中间花粉管
There will be a joint-like thing appearing at the tip
尖端会有一个合状的东西出现
Let's say you're like a normal pollen tube
比如说你像正常的花粉管
it grows like this
它是这样生长
it will keep growing
它会不断地往前生长
But when your gene happens
但是当你这个基因发生
When you let this protein express in large quantities
你大量让这个蛋白质表现的时候
Pollen tube growth stops
花粉管生长停止了
Then you can find that the pollen tubes grow
然后你可以发现在花粉管生长
In the middle of this process, there is a particularly bright
这过程中间有一个这个特别亮的
Our protein creates a
我们的蛋白质会造成一个
a so-called aggregation of thinking
一个所谓的维思的聚集
This will affect the pollen tube
这样子呢就会影响到花粉管
It will prevent the pollen tube from continuing to grow.
就会让花粉管没有办法继续的生长
So use this way
所以利用这样子的方式
we just know
我们就知道
Our protein may be a Wisdom-binding protein
我们的蛋白质可能是一个维思结合蛋白质
it for it throughout the pollen tube
它对于它在整个花粉管
It must go through the growth process
生长过程它必须要经过
very fine regulation
非常细微的一个调控
so this is a
所以这是一个
Another one we just talked about
另外一个我们刚才讲到
A pollination of whole pollen
整个花粉的一个受粉的作用
we want to know
我们是希望了解到
How does pollen grow in the word dimension
花粉到底怎麼在詞維裡面生長
Because all of our current literature above
因為我們現在所有的文獻上面
All of us, like what we just said
我們所有 比如說我們剛剛講的
The Arab world has a lot of information on the Internet
阿拉伯界有很多網路上的資料
These are all from the incubator
這一些都是從在培養機裡面
growing pollen hall
生長的花粉館所得到的
then we were thinking
那我們就在想
The pollen hall grows inside the style
那花粉館它長是在花柱裡面
why you can find out
為什麼 你可以去發現
We grow in in vitro culture machine
我們在體外培養機生長的
and internally grown pollen pavilions
和體內生長的花粉館
The first pollen pavilion grown inside the body
第一個 在體內生長的花粉館
grow very fast
長得非常的快
Iron Lily
比如說鐵爆百合
its from stigma to style to its fat
它的從柱頭到花柱到它的脂肪
The middle can be up to about 15 cm
中間最長可以大概15公分
It can grow from head to tail in two days
兩天它就可以從頭長到尾
But the incubator you grow in vitro
但是你在體外培養的培養機
never last that long
永遠長不了那麼長
can't grow so fast
也長不了那麼快
The other one is in Iron Explosion Lily
另外一個就是在鐵爆百合
we can find out
我們可以發現
growing in the stylet
在花柱裡面生長的
it attaches to each other
它會彼此的附著在一起
Not only attached to each other
不僅彼此附著在一起
will also be tightly attached to the so-called
也會緊緊的附著在所謂的
emits a surface of this layer
發出這一層表面的一個
a cell called the epidermal
一個叫做 epidermal 表皮細胞
so we were thinking
所以我們就在想
Is it growing in vitro or in vivo?
是不是體內體外生長
the only difference
唯一差別的哪裡
Teeth
齒瑞
Is it the one played by Gary?
是不是齒瑞所扮演的一個
what kind of role
什麼樣的一個角色
because of some materials
因為一些材料的關係
so there's been no way anyone would know
所以一直沒有辦法有人知道
these pollen tubes
這些花粉管
what's going on in the body
在體內到底是怎麼樣
so a few years ago
所以在幾年以前呢
we used a special method
我們就用了一個特別的方式
let's just let this
我們就讓這個
We constructed a transplant pig material
我們構築了一個轉植豬材料
It uses pollen-specific proteins
它用花粉專一表現的蛋白質
received a call
接到一個叫做
ribosomal protein
核糖體的蛋白質
Ribosomes, do you remember?
核糖體你記不記得
At first, what I just said earlier
最早我剛剛前面講的
from genes not most
是從基因 不是最
what messenger to use
用什麼 messenger
message messenger
訊息 messenger
from the nucleus to the cytoplasm
在從細胞核送到細胞質
ribosome
不是要經過核糖體
final protein
最後產生蛋白質
the ribosomal protein
這個核糖體蛋白質
So we put this protein
所以我們把這個蛋白質
how about after showing
表現出來以後怎麼樣
Because if you think about it, all the genes are going to come from
因為你想想看所有的基因都是要從
Gene to Messenger
基因到Messenger
Messenger ends up in the ribosome
Messenger最後會在核糖體
So of course we our
所以我們當然我們這個
When ribosomes can be labeled
可以把核糖體標示的時候
Let's use Country again
我們再用Country
This ribosome can contain the incoming
可以把這個核糖體上面含有正在轉入的
The message RNA precipitates it all together
訊息RNA把它一起沉澱下來
At this time we use this way
這個時候我們用這樣的方式
What we can find is inside the style
我們可以找到是在花柱裡面
protein inside growing pollen tube
生長的花粉管裡面的蛋白質
And with a so-called
而用這樣子所謂的一個
Non-destructive we have something called Translator
非破壞性的我們有一個叫做Translator
That is to say, some of the message RNA
也就是說這一些的訊息RNA
inside the pollen tube
正在花粉管裡面
A message inside a growing pollen tube
正在生長的花粉管裡面的一個訊息
this we can find
這個我們就可以找到
what kind of protein
有哪一些蛋白質
Which gene products of this process
哪一些基因產品的這個過程
Also we can find
還有我們可以發現
This gene is really fun
這個基因真的很好玩
This is normal Wildtide
這是正常的Wildtide
you can spot a pollen tube
你可以發現一個花粉管
Will only meet from a micro
只會從一個micro拜見
But when you some
但是当你某些这里面
We find these genes
我们找到这些基因
to find its mutant
去找到它的突变株的发现
its pollen tube
它的花粉管
The first pig's mouth that couldn't find Chi Rui
第一个找不到池蕊的猪口
or that it will pass through
或者是说它会过门不入
additional or multiple pollen tubes
另外或者有多个花粉管
So this is basically
所以这基本上
when these are in the pollen
当这些在花粉里面
gene generation
大量表现的基因发生
when mutation
突变的时候
The whole behavior of your pollen tubes
你的花粉管的整个行为
changed
就发生了改变
another one
另外一个
A student from one of our most recent labs
我们最近一个实验室的学生
what he does is
他做的就是
we found so many
我们找到这么多
one of them
其中有一个
this gene
这个基因
it is involved as well
它是参与的也是
Related to Raboson synthesis
跟Raboson合成有关
But when your gene mutates
但是当你这个基因发生突变的时候
You can discover the structure of the entire pollen tube
你可以发现整个花粉管的结构
The structure of this cell currency
这个细胞幣的结构
or the inner cytoskeleton
或者是里面细胞骨架维施的
have changed
都发生了改变
Finally, I would like to introduce to you a
最后我要跟各位介绍一个
gene transfer technology
就是基因转值技术
We just talked about TDNA
我们刚才讲过TDNA
This is what we rely on, Mr. Ermin
這是我們所賴兒民老師
he is the expert
他是這個專家
Actually I don't really understand
其實我並不是很懂
If you really want to change jobs on this
你們真的要對這個轉職的話
go to him
去找他
He must give you a very perfect answer
他一定給你一個非常完美的答案
But what kind of sex is this
但是這個是一個什麼樣性的
That is to say, we are in the plant of Agrobacterium
就是說我們在農感菌這個植物
this pathogen
這個病原菌
We found out that it has something called TiPlasma
我們發現它有一個叫做TiPlasma
plastid
質體
This thing is very special
這個東西很特別的是
We can do something on it
我們可以在上面做一些
do something
做一些東西
This TiPlasma will eventually
這個TiPlasma最後會
pinch pinch see first come
掐 掐 看先到
will be delivered to the plant
會送到植物體裡面
Then look inside the genes of the plants first
然後看先到植物的基因裡面
top of gene body
基因體上面
will then result in a
然後會造成一個
It can make it grow and mutate
可以讓它長生突變
can also
也可以
Sew in
縫階的插進去
Can cause a certain gene in the plant to be destroyed
可以造成植物體某一個基因會破壞掉
so we talk
所以我們講的
The TiPlasma mutant just mentioned
剛剛講的TiPlasma突變株
Or you can make a gene
或者是說你可以讓某一個基因
massive performance
大量表現
This is one I found on the Internet
這個是我在網路上找出來的一個
It is TiPlasma
就是TiPlasma
You can put the gene you want
你可以把你要的這一段基因
put in
放進去
then send it
然後就送到
In this so-called concentrated bacteria
這個所謂的濃感菌裡面
Concentrated bacteria?
濃感菌呢
Then you can use it to infect plants
然後你可以用它來感染植物
you can use it to infect plants
你可以用它來感染植物
What about after you infect the plant?
你感染植物以後呢
this is a normal operation
這是一個正常操作
What about after infecting plants?
感染植物以後呢
This highly sensitive bacterium will use a special structure
這個濃感菌會用一個特別的一個構造
will put the so-called TiPlasma
會把所謂的這個TiPlasma
into the plant
送到植物裡面
well you get infected
好 你就感染
The Ecopter is attached to the cell wall of this plant
就Ecopter附著在這個植物的細胞壁
when it attaches to the plant cell wall
當它附著在植物細胞壁以後
What about this TiPlasma?
這個TiPlasma呢
it enters the cell
它就會進到細胞
then run to the cell wall
然後會跑到細胞壁
Then the whole of your gene
然後整個你這個基因
with this thing it carries
就它上面所攜帶的這個東西
You can shoot first in the whole gene's
就可以槍先在整個基因的
TiTiA will pick up here
TiTiA就會接在這個地方
entire
整個
so you can make genes
所以你可以造成基因
Genetic
差不多地方可能造成基因的
a destruction of
的一個破壞
So you might be causing what's called a mutation
所以你可能就造成所謂的突變
then you end up
然後你最後
Previous words could be generated using
以前的話是可以可能用產生的
tissue culture
用所謂的組織培養
Then you from tissue culture can finally generate
然後你從組織培養最後可以產生
Then your tissue culture
然後你這個組織培養
Your DNA has a
你這個DNA上面有一個
For example, the volition potion of sand herb potion
比如說沙草劑的意志劑
when you spray sand
那你在噴沙草劑的時候
as long as you have a job change
你只要有轉職的時候
it's anti-weed
它就可以抗沙草劑
so you know it
所以你就知道它
in such a way
用這樣的一個方式的話
we can do it at last
我們最後就可以來做
so we were a few years ago
所以我們在幾年前
We have a way like this
我們有用這樣的一個方式
Let's go
我們去
because in the Arab world it is a
因為在阿拉伯界它是一個
There is a nice support library
有一個很好的支援庫
called DNA Library
叫做DNA Library
let's go find
我們去找
At that time we were interested in saying
那時候我們有興趣的是說
when your seed
當你這個種子
when you chicken mutant pig
當你這個雞突變豬
As long as it has no so-called homologous offspring
它只要沒有所謂的同源後代
It only has Historzygone
它只有Historzygone
That is to say, if its homologous descendants
也就是說它的同源後代的話
when you plant
當你這個植物
There are two DNA's in it
有兩個DNA的在這裡面
homologous offspring
同源後代
What does the absence of this homologous offspring mean?
沒有這同源後代表示什麼
There will be a problem with your configuration body
你的配置體就會有問題
So you can't spawn poor people or plants
所以你不能產生窮人或植物
or yours
或者是你的
There is a problem with the entire embryonic development
整個胚胎發育有問題
So we use a strategy like this
所以我們利用這樣子的一個策略
We found quite a few genes
我們找到了相當多的基因
it's basically
它基本上
This is the development of the whole embryo
這是整個胚胎的發育
we discover
我們發現
Quite a few are related to embryonic development
相當多是跟胚胎發育有關
It's a normal spider
這是正常的蜘蛛
you can find
你可以發現
it will be ten weeks different
它會不同的十星期
But we take this gene
但是我們當這個基因
when a gene is mutated
某一個基因發生突變的時候
you can find
你可以發現
It turned out to be the so-called WATER
原來是所謂的WATER
is in the Hard stage
是在Hard stage
At this time it is basically
這時候它根本上
There is a problem with the whole development
整個發育就有問題
so we know that means
所以我們知道是說
say it in this way
用這樣的方式說
This gene is involved in
這個基因是參與到
throughout embryonic development
整個胚胎發育中的
a certain process
某一個過程
we have been in the past
我們在過去這一段時間
We probably found quite a few
我們大概找到了相當多
You can find that it may be following
你可以發現它可能在跟
Embryo magnet development
胚磁體的發育
One related to cell division
跟細胞分裂有關的有一個
In addition or some of the cells
另外或者是細胞裡面的一些
or nuclear RNA metabolism
或者是核的RNA的代謝
e.g. RNA
比如說RNA
Methanageal RNA to be produced
MethanagealRNA要產生
to go through so called some nuclei
要經過所謂的一些接核
Add a Polyase to the whole process
加一个Polyase整个过程
the process it participates in
它所参与的那过程
What about the third one?
第三个呢
is to affect the so-called
就是影响到所谓的
Endome Memet trafficking
Endome Memet trafficking
For example, the cytoskeleton we just talked about
像比如说我们刚刚讲的细胞骨架
those proteins like this
那些蛋白质像这一类的
So we use the time in the past
所以我们利用在过去这段时间呢
we are probably
我们大概就是
There is quite a bit of research
有相当多的一个研究
say we are here
比如说我们在这里
We can find that it is possible to
我们可以发现可能跟
on the ribose base
在核糖底的
The brevity of that RNA or
那个RNA的简洁或者是
nuclear human development
核人的发育
or a
或者是一个
with these
跟这些
Or Endome Memet trafficking
或者是Endome Memet trafficking
When your gene discovers
当你这个基因发现
when mutation
突变的时候
You can find the whole different package
你可以发现整个异包
changes in growth
的生长都发生改变
So probably this is our past
所以大概这个是我们过去
we were
我们在过
We're mostly following the development of pollen
我们主要是在跟花粉的发育
then fertilized
然后受精
And finally we now also follow
然后最后我们现在也跟
planting development
种植的发育有关
this is us in the past
这是我们在过去
During this time we mainly do
这段时间我们主要是做的
Finally, I want to tell you that
最后我要跟大家讲就是说
In basic research we often ask
基础研究我们常常问
what's the use of you doing that
你做那个有什么用
In fact, the Basic Research Institute
其實基礎研究院
I feel like we are here today
我覺得今天我們在這裡
professional research institute
的專業研究院
should say
應該說
I should thank professional institute
我應該感謝專業研究院
give me a place to fulfill my dreams
給我一個地方來完成我的夢想
i probably from college
我大概從大學
until the Ph.D.
一直到念博士班
I'm probably doing this basic research
我大概都是做這個基礎研究
But I think it's really a
但是我覺得這真的是一個
very interesting one
非常有趣的一個
a subject
一個課題
then the second we are here
然後第二個我們在這裡
I think I have another mission
我覺得我還有另外一個使命
in this education
在這個教育
we are in the middle of this process
我們在這個過程中間
We have trained a considerable number of doctoral students
我們有培育的相當多的博士班的學生
postdoctoral fellow
博士後
Or say we have bred
或者是比如說我們有培育的
PhD students
博士班學生
later returned to their country
後來回到他們國家
Costa Rica
有個在克斯達里加
He is now an assistant professor
他現在當助理教授
We have a postdoctoral fellow at Pingtung University of Science and Technology
我們有個博士後在屏東科技大學
We have a postdoc in the US
我們有個博士後在美國
find a politics professor
找到一個政治教授
These are a mission we are here
這些都是一個我們在這裡的一個mission
so i think it is
所以我覺得是
What is the role of industry
產業有什麼作用
I want to eat is a good one
我想吃吃是一個很好的一個
Five Fingers Watermelon
五指西瓜
five fingers watermelon we use
五指西瓜我們利用
For example we can generate
比如說我們可以產生
pistil
雌蕊的
double generation
複代
triploid pistil
雌蕊這個三倍體
Then the male is diploid
然後這個雄的是二倍體
We ended up using pollen tubes
我們最後利用花粉管
when fertilized
受精的時候
cause the fruit to expand
會造成這個果實的膨大
But the fruit
但是這個果實的
Seeds cannot be produced
種子沒辦法產生
so what's the end result
所以最後達到什麼
double silver
雙銀
Consumers do not need to repaint after eating
消費者吃東西不用再塗
don't paint that paper
不要塗那個紙
right
對不對
but you use
但是你利用
To buy this seed from a seed company
要向種子公司買這個種子
because it has no seeds
因為它沒有種子
You can't respond to the next generation
你反應不了下一代
so i want to say
所以我想說
While you're in the middle of this process
當你整個這個過程中間
you understand
你了解了
you have a chance like this
你就有這樣子的一個機會
like i just said
就像我剛剛講的
You can produce these with flowers within flowers
你可以產到花中有花的這些
I think that's what we know
我想這就是我們知識的
a cumulative
一個累積
One result we can have
我們可以有的一個結果
Finally I think I'd like to thank you
最後我想我要謝謝
is ours
就是我們的
over the past few years
在過去這一幾年來
This is the first few years
這是最早前幾年來
then it's the two of us
然後這是我們兩個
mathematics student
數學生
These two high school students seem to win prizes at every science fair they attend
這兩個高中生好像參加所有的科展都得獎
Probably going well is to be able to represent Taiwan to participate in the international science and technology exhibition
大概順利就是要可能代表台灣去參加國際科展吧
And then here's our executive team
然後這是我們的行政團隊
Today I want to thank this Tingyu
今天我要謝謝這個庭裕
The three organizations he does today
他今天做的這三個組織
He was the one who did the tissue training in the Shihu Lake
那個石湖南的那個組織培養就是他做的
And then here's our administrative team across the command post
然後這是我們整個指揮所的行政團隊
Our Research Assistants
我們的研究助技師
I don't think there are some
我想沒有這一些
So we need supplies for the logistics force
所以我們要有的後勤部隊的補給
Only then can we do some research ahead
我們才能夠在前面往前從做些研究
And finally thanks to the Ministry of Science and Technology
然後最後要謝謝科技部
And our Academia Sinica
還有我們中央研究院
Cheviso and this agricultural development center
持維索還有這個農業發展中心
All of this is a financial subsidy for us
這個所有的給我們的一個經費上的一個補助
i think i'll stop here for today
我想我今天的時間就到這裡
Fortunately, everyone didn't sleep too much.
還好大家沒有睡得太厲害
Then I welcome you if you have any questions
然後有什麼問題我就歡迎你們
Thanks
謝謝
Well, we thank Dr. Zhao for a very good presentation
好 我們謝謝趙博士非常精彩的演講
so we now open the question
那我們現在時間開放問題
Work hard everyone, the public album will mention it to him on April 1
努力大家 公共影集跟他四一提到
say yes we have a little gift for the speakers
說是我們有一點小禮物給發言者
On the side of the question asked, Mr. Zhao still has
發問的問題的這邊 趙老師還是有
still have
還是有
Responsibilities of our position
我們職位所的責業
There is an introduction to us above and our
有介紹我們上面還有我們的
Information from our Facebook page
Facebook我們的網頁的資訊
Welcome everyone, ginseng can come
歡迎大家人參可以來
good
好
Excuse me, there are bear flowers and snake flowers
請問一下花有熊花跟蛇花
So how did the source of what is called a false flower come from?
那什麼叫做假性花的來源是怎麼來的
What
什麼
false flower
假性花
Generally speaking, we
一般來講的話就是說我們
we have bisexual flowers
我們有雙性花
That is to say, this kind of flower has tooth stamen and bear stamen
就是說這種花有齒蕊熊蕊
this is normal
這是一般正常的
There's a so-called bear stamen
那裡有一個就是所謂的持熊蕊
holding bear example like corn
持熊譬如說像玉米
its pistil is on top
它的熊蕊是在上面
Its stamens are at the bottom
它的齒蕊是在下
So this is two generations called unisexual flowers
所以這個就是兩個分代叫單性花
I'm not very clear about false flowers
假性花我就並不是很清楚
So this is according to
所以這個就是依照
this is the same flower
這就是同一個花
it has a sex
它有一個性別
we call bisexual flowers
我們叫雙性花
If you want unisexual flowers
要單性花的話
That is, Chi Wei and Xiong Wei are separated
就是齒瑋雄瑋是分開的
yes
是
teacher sorry
老師 不好意思
Just now you mentioned that
剛才您有提到說
you used to take that pollen tube
你曾經把那個花粉管
Yes, the pollen tube grows by itself
是 說花粉管它自己會長
it you cut it off
它你把它切掉
because we need sperm
因為我們精子是需要
a humid space
濕潤的一個空間嘛
in a humid environment
濕潤的一個環境裡面
Yeah so I'll tell you which one are you talking about
對 所以我講你講哪一個
Because what I just said
因為我剛剛講的就
because when you said cut off
因為你說切掉的時候
I'm sending it will it dry?
我是發 它會不會乾掉
very good right
很好 對
I didn't speak very carefully just now
我剛剛沒有講得很仔細
that means we are the first
就是說我們第一個
We're going to make pollen, lean powder about 24
我們要讓花粉 瘦粉大概24
about 12 hours to 24 hours
大概12個小時到24小時
maybe i know where it grows
大概我知道它大概長到哪裡
At this time, after you cut off
這個時候你切掉以後
you need to seal it up
你上面要把它封口
Or paint with decorative bells to prevent moisture from evaporating
或塗繁飾鈴 防止水分蒸發
this is what needs to be done
這個是需要做的
but you just
但是你只要
you don't care how much you cut
你不管你切的多少
as long as you can maintain
你只要能夠維持
because it is in the whole pollen hall
因為它在整個花粉館
grow in style
在花柱裡面生長
it keeps forming
它不斷會形成
I was talking about Keris Pluck
我剛講的叫Keris Pluck
it can be a totally pollen house
它可以是一個完全可以把花粉館
The most active place at the front
最前面最active的那個地方
seal it up completely
完全把它封住
you just keep that place
你只要維持那個地方
Don't destroy the whole pollen hall
不要破壞到整個花粉館
It can deliver two gold cells to embryonic pigs
它就可以把兩個金細胞送到胚豬
complete double fertilization
完成雙重受精
so amazing
所以很神奇
So it means it will
所以它就是說它會
it pollen house will know
它花粉館會知道
will feel the pool class
會感受到池類
Embryo sac
應該說胚囊
send a message like this
送出來這樣的訊息
to attract it to grow
來吸引它生長
At once
就
we just talked about emptiness
我們剛講說以空
like iron lily
就是像鐵爆百合
it belongs to the style of the stroke
它是屬於中風的花柱
It's actually filled with liquid
它的裡面事實上是充滿了液體
we call it from
我們叫做它會從
Its front capital is divided into
它前面的柱頭上面分在
Our name is Standard Exte
我們叫做Standard Exte
it keeps going from the bottom
它不斷的會從底部
secrete something like this
分泌出這樣的東西出來
still have this
還是會有這種
yes still
對 還是有
But pollen tubes are actually fun
但花粉管其實是很好玩的
That means it's just been pollinated on the stigma
就是說它剛剛受粉在柱頭上
grow and grow into the style
生長 然後長到花柱裡面的
for a while
一段時間的時候呢
it needs its own nourishment
它是需要自己的養分
So it's a pollen tube, you go straight to the inside
所以它花粉管你直接去看裡面
it has a lot of oil bodies
它有很多的油體
There is still a lot of Starch
還有很多的Starch
starch liquid
就是澱粉液體
But wait until it grows in the style for a while
但是等到它在花柱裡面生長一段時間
it will be from
它會要從
Sirac is here to absorb nutrients
Sirac這裡來吸收養分
yes
是
in the video just now
剛剛的影片裡面
It says that the DNA is not there are four of that
它有說那個DNA不是有四個那個
to combine?
去組合嗎
Then it itself will delete what it says it doesn't want
然後它自己本身會刪掉說它不要的
So have you learned from this
那你們有沒有從這裡面去學習到說
how does the plant itself go about removing
它植物本身如何去刪除
because we now have
因為我們現在有會
Is there any progress on this?
那這方面有沒有什麼進度啊
Is there any technology in this area?
這個方面有沒有什麼技術
Our current results are as far as I know
我們現在的的成績就我所了解的話
Yes know we have a program called
是知道我們有一個叫做
A mechanism of splicing to do these donations
splicing的一個機制去做這些捐獎
if you are interested
如果你們有興趣的話
We recently had a teacher named Tu Shilong in our Institute of Botany
我們植物所最近有一個老師叫圖士龍
He posted an article on Plain cell last month
他在去上個月在Plain cell發了一篇
Just to tell you what this mechanism will affect
就是告訴你說這個機制它會影響到什麼
it may take to plants affected by light
它可能采取到植物受到光的影響
will affect flowering
會影響到開花
This is an article from our recent teacher
這是我們所最近老師的一個文章
It is to do this so-called splicing mechanism
它就是做這個所謂的splicing這個機制
If you have a chance, you can go and find out
你有機會的話你可以去去了解看一看
Thanks
謝謝
The two techniques I've heard are
就是我聽到的兩個技術是
One is strong and the other is
一是精強跟另外一個是
That female dragon feels like you have a body
那個用女龍感覺你帶一隻體
into plant cells
進到植物細胞裡面
Is there any other way to create a picture group
那有沒有其他的可以製造出圖片組的方式
For example, the recent hot gene editing and the like
例如最近滿火紅的基因編輯之類的
Gene editing is right
基因編輯這個也對
yes
沒錯
This is a good mechanism
這個是一個很好的機制
It's a system that uses CRISPR
就是用 CRISPR 的一個系統
The so-called TDNA
那個所謂的TDNA
What is the benefit of this system of insertion or CRISPR
插入或 CRISPR這個系統的好處是什麼
you know where you insert
你知道你插入的地方
Also we have a mutant technology called EMS
另外我們有一個叫做 EMS 是一個突變技
You can treat something like this with the seeds from which it was planted
你可以用把它植物的種子處理這樣的東西
You can see that it might be breaking a certain clip of DNA
你可以發現它可能是把某一個DNA的剪輯破壞掉
You can cause Point Mutation
你可以造成 Point Mutation
When you Point Mutation is you three
當你 Point Mutation 就是你三個
You alone decide on an amino acid
你一個才會決定一個胺基酸
You may be at the end after you put this Point Mutation mutation
你可能在最後你把這個 Point Mutation 突變以後
it should keep doing it
它應該繼續做下去
it stops here
它在這裡就停止
so you gene it has no way to complete one to produce a complete
所以你基因它沒有辦法完成一個產生一個完整的
but this thing you
但是這個東西你就
We call it Mapping
我們叫做 Mapping
you don't know which gene
你不知道哪一個基因
backcross
你不斷的要經過回交
But this can also be done
但是這個也可以做
can also do
也可以做
But that is to say, it is slower
但是就是說這個就比較慢
is this another one
這是另外一個嗎
What you just said is also a way
你剛剛講的那個也是一個方式
now there are quite a few
現在有相當多
A gene gun is basically just a
基因槍基本上只是一個
We are called Train Sink
我們叫做Train Sink
not a stable offspring
不是穩定的後代
it's just for a short time you're in a certain
它只是短時間你在某一個
For example, today
比如說其實今天
In addition, what we just said is called
另外我們剛剛講的叫做
we can work
我們可以從業子
called protoplasts
叫做原生質體叫Protoplas
you can go with some genes
你可以用一些基因去
fleeting performance
短暫的表現
but this one has two
但是這個有兩個
Your brief performance is actually
你這個短暫表現事實上
you may be too short the first time
你可能第一個時間太短
You didn't grow to say a few weeks
你沒有長到比如說幾個禮拜
You don't get through the whole development process
你沒不到整個發育的過程
This is a
這是一個
The second process of your Train Sink
第二個你這種Train Sink的過程
You would put, for example, in a normal cell
你會把比如說在正常的細胞裡面
maybe only 100 proteins
可能只有100個蛋白質
You Train Sink go down
你這Train Sink下去
give it 10,000 protein
給它1萬個蛋白質
it is more than itself
它就超過它本身
so you see something
所以你看到的東西
sometimes you don't know
有的時候你不知道
It turned out to be a rather troublesome one.
原先真的这是一个比较麻烦的
So we sometimes experiment
所以我们有的时候做实验
We would prefer the so-called
我们会比较喜欢所谓的
stable line
stable line
after turning around
就是用转经之后
We're not even going to use a
我们甚至不是要用一个
Driving values ​​for a large number of representations
大量表现的驱动值
Let this gene be expressed in large quantities
让这个基因大量表现
We're going to use its own drive value instead
我们反而要用它自己的驱动值
what is its own driving value
它自己的驱动值是什么
it at a certain time
它在某一个时间
The amount of performance will be very precisely controlled
表现的量都会非常的精确的控制
let's take a look
我们来看一看
For example, the protein value
比如说把这个蛋白值
silver light protein
接上一个银光蛋白
Let's see where it behaves
我们看它在什么地方表现
will it help you on something
它会不会帮你在什么包气上面
These we can do research on
这些我们可以去做研究
so we sometimes
所以我们有的时候
You have to be very precise to control these things
你必须要很精控地去控制这些东西
is there any problem
还有没有什么问题
I just saw that
刚才我才看到说
This little Liu is a set of black hole postcards
这个小刘是黑洞明信片一组
very good
非常好
Does he know about black holes?
他知道黑洞嘛
it's us
是我们这个
With this very bright spot Zhongyuanyuan
搭着这个非常亮点中原院
Cooperate with all over the world
跟世界各地合作的
so we must strive
所以一定要争取
still a few
还好几张
i want to ask questions
我都想问问题
I want to ask
我想請教一下
that for example
那個比如說是
The pollen house that the teacher said
老師說的那個花粉館
In this way, the seed can be produced
這樣子的話可以產生那個種子
Matching strain
配株
ask me like this
請問一下這樣子的話
For example, our guava
比如說我們那個芭樂
Suppose its seed has 100 flowers
假如說它的那個種子有100粒的花
like this
這樣子的話
Is it the pollen of every pollen house
是不是每一個花粉館的花粉
both from the same
都是同樣來自
The other ones also come from the same flower
另外都同樣來自一朵的
it's the gold here thank you
就是金子這邊謝謝
So this thing we will
所以這個東西我們就
actually very similar
其實很像
For example, you say we
比如說你說我們
Is it yours that can be told in another way?
是不是你的可以從另外講說
Did we generate those plants with bad heads all the same?
我們是不是產生的那些植物頭壞的都一樣
you can ask
你可以這樣問
In fact, we say that we are all the same
其實我們比如說我們都是同
Our brothers and sisters unless you are a twin today
我們的弟兄姊妹除非你今天是雙胞胎
Otherwise, you will be different from your brothers and sisters
要不然你跟著弟兄姊妹都不一樣
So the same pollen house
所以同樣的花粉館
fertilization process
受精的過程
its last so-called single back bottom
它最後所謂的單背底
With the single back, they will have the so-called dye combination
跟單背底他們會有所謂的染色結合
when together
合在一起的時候
This intermediate chromosome will call
這中間染色體會呼喚
many things will happen
會發生很多很多的事情
So we sometimes do experiments
所以我們有的時候做實驗出來
will find
會發現
You can see every pollen store
你可以看每一個花粉館所
The seed produced by fertilization is a single individual
受精產生的種子是單一的個體
Every seed behaves differently
每一個種子的表現都不一樣
you all look the same
你看起來好像都一樣
right? people all look the same
對不對 人看起來都一樣
everyone is different
是大家都不一樣
You are different from your brothers and sisters
你跟你的弟兄姊妹不一樣
you go and see
你去看
Every seed is like your brothers and sisters
每一個種子就像你弟兄姊妹一樣
looks like seeds
看起來都是種子
But their reactions are totally different
但是他們的反應完全不一樣
So really throughout
所以真的是在整個
so what good is it
所以這樣有什麼好處
When your plant goes through what is called a chromosome
當你的植物經過所謂的染色體
The pair calls for these
的配對呼喚這些
bullets you spawn
你產生的子彈
there will always be one
總會有一個
when your environment is not suitable
當你的環境不適合的時候
Maybe under these 1000 seeds
說不定在這1000個種子底下
have one or two
有一個兩個
can survive
可以活得下去
so your species
所以你這個物種
Only then can we continue to react
可以才不斷的反應下去
Like the Iron Lily we just talked about
像我們剛剛講的鐵爆百合
Iron Lily Seeds
鐵爆百合的種子
if i count
我如果去算
A seed of an iron blast lily grown out of a flower
一個花瘦出來的鐵爆百合的種子
so quite a lot
500個
but each made
但是每一個做出來的
Probably not the same
大概都不太一樣
So this fun place is
所以這個好玩的地方就在
So sometimes we make mutant beads
所以有時候我們做的突變珠
You see, this is a mutant strain of the pollen tube
你看這是花粉館的突變珠
you should think it's gonna die
你應該就覺得它會死
but it's weird
但是很奇怪
I don't know I don't understand now
我不知道現在我也是不太明白
life always will
生命總是會
will find its way out
會找出它的出路
it will always have in you
你這個裡面它總是會有
Five or six seeds will be able to bear fruit
五六個種子會可以結
So you can keep doing time
所以你還可以繼續做時間下去
so fun
所以很好玩
its not all dead
它不是全部都死
it means you are an arab
它就是說你一個阿拉伯界
Can produce fifty or sixty flowers
可以結五六十個花
One flower can bear fifty or sixty seeds
一個朵花可以結五六十個種子
but you are important
但是你當你很重要的
severe mutant beads
嚴重的突變珠
there are always a few seeds left
總是還有幾個種子
you can keep doing
你可以繼續做
A lot of fun
很好玩
I don't know why
原因我不知道
this is what we actually
這就是我們其實
we always wanted
我們一直想要
also want to know
也想要去了解
Why
為什麼
Thank you, excellent talk
Thank you, excellent talk
i want to ask
我想問一下
You want to talk about an iron cannon board
你要講一個鐵砲板
Is it native to Taiwan?
是屬於台灣的原生種嗎
Is it Nectar Lili?
是Nectar Lili嗎
iron cannon board
鐵砲板
I use East Lili
我用的是East Lili
we want to find out now
我們現在想要去找找看
We know when there is essence
我們知道有精華時算
There are also medical treatments that cannot be let go
也有放不去的醫療
With medical treatment and discounts
有醫療和有優惠
very close to lilly
非常接近利利
So if your research
所以你這個研究的話
You use this seed in Taiwan
你們在台灣是用這個種子
is the seed of Taiwan
是台灣的種子
or bio-decoration seeds for sale
還是當賣的生物裝飾的種子
The iron cannon box we used before
我們之前用的鐵砲擺盒
Is East Lily
是East Lily
basically bought by the seed company
基本上是種子公司買的
But in the future we will use
但是我們未來會用
What I just said will use Taiwan
剛剛講的會用台灣的
Taiwan box
台灣擺盒
among us
我們當中還有
Another No. 1 Taiwan pendulum box
台灣擺盒另外一號
These are the ones I use now
現在用的這些
Commercial of these East Lily
commercial的這些East Lily
It is self incompatible
它是self incompatible
That is to say, my own flowers are not able to
就是說自己的花本不能夠
receive flowers produce flowers
受到花本產生花本
But Taiwan's display box is very special
但是台灣擺盒很特別
it can
它可以
So it gives us another big
所以它給我們另外一個很大的
yes i want to ask him
對 我想問他
common environment is
普通的环境是
environmental
环境或是环境的
is different
是不同的
OK Taiwan Lily is basically found in the mountains
OK 台湾百合基本上是在山区发现的
But we can grow in the greenhouse
但是我们可以在温室种
We also did Xiao Xiang here
我们也做过小祥在这里
We could have done it last time too
我们上次也可以做过
We self-pollinate to produce
我们自花受粉可以产生
received quite a lot of fruit
收到相当多的果实
probably too
大概也是
it can receive hundreds no problem
它可以收到几百个 没问题
so we have been doing
所以我们有在做
So it's like a worm cage
所以说像肉虫笼
or that ginger
或者是那个姜
Its flowering is the same as Lily's
它的开花是跟莉莉是
this chicken is the same
这个鸡子是一样的
sorry i really don't know that
对不起 那个我真的不知道
OK
OK
Thanks
谢谢
Seems like this black hole is funny
好像这个黑洞很有笑
I was asked just now
刚刚前面这一会问到了
actually quite interesting
其实相当有趣
I would love to ask about flowering plants
我很想请教开花的植物
some are blossoming in the industry
有些是在业界开花
is it possible to change
有没有可能改变
make it bloom by day
讓它變成白天開花
Of course I think this is for example
當然我覺得這個就是比如說
You can be like our director
你可以就像我們在座所長
What he does is related to light
他做的是跟光有關的
Light can regulate flowering
光可以調節開花
you can make these changes
你可以可以去做這些改變
But I miss Ye Lai Xiang
但是我想夜來鄉
If you let it open during the day, I don’t know if it smells good or not
你讓它白天開我就不知道它香不香
So I feel this thing
所以我就覺得這個東西
We knew you could change into one of its shapes
我們就知道你可能改變到它某一個形狀
but you may lose other
但是你可能會失去了其他的
So I think it's a lot
所以我覺得這有很多尊
We may need improvement as a whole
我們可能是整體要需要改良
is there any good for us doing this
我們這樣子做有沒有什麼好處
so i think sometimes
所以我覺得有的時候
But actually I think we sometimes
但其實我是覺得我們有的時候
when we're all doing
我們現在所有在做的時候
We are the caretakers who discover its creation
我們是發現那個照護者它的創造
we are not inventing we are discovering
我們不是在發明 我們在發現
But its discovery must have its uses
但是它的發現大概一定有它的用處
So I can say that it should be possible to make this adjustment
所以可以我想說應該是可以做這個調節
Even we say they have done a lot
甚至我們說他們有做很多的
How to tune with light for flowering
跟光怎麼樣去調供開花
But this we basically understand its mechanism
但是這個我們基本上是了解到它的機制
But I don't think it does
但是我好像它沒有
I don't know if there is such an attempt in the future to make
我不知道未來是不是有這種企圖可以讓
Arab worlds bloom at night
阿拉伯界都在晚上開花
but i don't know what's the use
但我不知道有什麼用
if there is no problem
沒有問題的話
Our black hole is about as fun as it gets.
我們那個黑洞也差不多好玩吧
So here's another
所以這邊還有一位
yes
是
study process
求學過程
I think
我覺得
not i think
不是我覺得
In fact, I have always liked biological things.
其實我本身我一直都很喜歡生物的東西
this
這個
And then the one that really let me pluck it in
然後真正讓我一頭摘進去的
I was very impressed that I was a freshman
我印象很深是我大一
i don't know what to do now
我不知道現在在做
I'm talking about my freshman year
我現在講我大一好了
university metropolis
大學都會
We used to have bank dances when we first entered college.
那時候我們大學剛進去都會有銀行舞會
right
對不對
You'll probably all go to the bank dance
你可能都會細上拜銀行舞會
We were also unavoidable that time
我們那次也不免俗的
Let's go to the bank dance
我們細上拜銀行舞會
you know us
你知道我們
Country kids are always shy
鄉下的孩子總是會害羞
I guess it's not fun
我想說好像沒什麼樂趣
He and I are above the theater
他我就在戲館上面
above our own theater
我們自己的戲館上面
There is a bright classroom
有一間教室亮
It turned out that a senior was doing an experiment
原來有個學長在做實驗
I'll go in and talk to him
我就進去跟他講
Senior, I'm just going to strike up a conversation anyway.
學長我就反正去搭訕
What are you doing
你在做什麼
After we're done talking, the dance is over.
等我們講完以後舞會結束
But from that day I knew
可是從那一天我就知道
i want to do research
我想要做研究
so i really didn't lie to you
所以我真的我沒有騙你
I study hard in college
大學我很認真的念書
everyone can
大家都可能
we play too, right?
我們也玩對不對
but also play
但是也玩
but we study hard
但是我們真的很認真的念書
Of course, you may be all about books
當然你可能都是書卷講
Why
為什麼
Because my senior told me
因為我學長跟我說
We are also very obedient
我們也很聽話
The senior said you want to apply to go abroad
學長說大學你要申請出國
your grades are better
你的成績要好
so how about good grades
所以成績要好怎麼樣
study
念書
so you play and play
所以你玩也是玩
but you know what you want
但是你知道你要什麼
so i finished college
所以我大學念完
Then go to graduate school
然後念研究所
then became a soldier
然後當了兵
After serving as a soldier
當完兵以後
because i know i'm in
因為我知道我在
I used to do it myself
我本身做的以前是
Comparing the traditional research on occupational science
比較傳統的職務學方面的研究
Don't know anything about molecular biology
對分子生物的東西不了解
i know that's a trend
我知道那是一個趨勢
So after I finish my military service
所以我當完兵以後呢
i served as a soldier at the youth headquarters
我在年輕總部當兵
it's very close
就是很近嘛
So after my young headquarters served as a soldier
所以我年輕總部當完兵以後
Come to Zhongying Yuan as a doppelganger
就來中營院分身所當
research assistant
研究助理
our same issue
我們同一期的
Later, they are our current colleagues
後來都是我們現在的同事
many
好多
So after two years as an assistant
所以當了兩年助理以後
study abroad
出國念書
So I've been all the way
所以我一路都是在
thanks for the grades
都是感謝成績
everything went well
都很順遂
I'm all over this
我都是在這個
environment of this study
這個研究的環境
research environment
研究的環境
because i just want
因為我就想
So I was in America
所以我當初我在美國
when you come back
要回來的時候
I also only apply for the position of the China Campus Institute
我也只申請中營院職威數
I didn't upgrade any other
我也沒有升級其他的
also really thank god
也真的感謝神
just came back
就回來了
Then it is really a very
然後在職位所真的是一個非常
In the future, I hope that all young students will have the opportunity
將來希望大家年輕的學生有機會
You can come to our job site to have a look
可以來我們職位所看一看
These teachers are really great.
真的這些老師都超級厲害的
They are many, many times stronger than me
都比我厲害很多很多倍
especially those new
尤其那些新的
you can get from everyone
你們可以從大家
like us
像我們
I just said after we got back here
我剛剛講過在我們這回來以後
we have all been
我們都一直
I think education is very important
我覺得教育是個很重要的
So I'm probably all except us math students
所以我大概就是除了我們數學生
we will take students number of students
我們會收學生數學生
Our program is very good
我們這個這個Program很好
Look at these two summer students
你看這兩個暑期生
the year before last year
去年前年的
they last
他們最後
We won our last games
我們最後的比賽都得到優勝
The two high school students I just talked about
那這兩個高中生我剛剛講的
They got awards
他們是拿的是獎狀
They are also participating in the National Science Fair
他們也是參加全國科展什麼
get this too
也是得到這個
so we have a lot of opportunities like this
所以我們有好多這樣的機會
able to attract students
能夠吸引學生來
I think this is probably us
我想這個大概就是我們
high school
高中就
high school i
高中我
I also participate in the biological society
我也是參加生物社
The senior generation participates in clubs and other high schools
高一代參加社等高
In the second-generation high school clubs, only the third-year students are studying
高二代社團只有高三在念書
So I didn't do very well
所以考得並不是很好
same is
一樣是
thanks for sharing
謝謝您分享
you just spoke
你剛剛講話
thank god twice
講了兩次感謝神
yes
是
so you're probably a christian
所以你大概是基督徒
i think that
我想那
sorry i'm a christian too
對不起 我也是基督徒
we in christian education we speak
我們在基督教育我們講說
Evolution and Creation
演化論跟創造論
in your experience
在你的經歷裡面
Who do you think is more likely to summon
你覺得誰比較像是傳召
In fact, I think evolution
其實我覺得演化論
your speech
你這個講話
actually stand by me
其實站在我
I think the theory of evolution is
我覺得演化論是有
I mean something about you
就是說你某一個東西
He can
他會
probably means
可能就是說
giraffe neck
比如長頸鹿的脖子
right
對不對
longer
再長
as long as in that environment
只要在那環境上
it's getting less and less
它越來越少
it's getting higher
它越來越高
But you said the giraffe was going to turn into a rhino
但是你說長頸鹿要變成犀牛
but a bit difficult
但是有點難
But the giraffe neck
但是長頸鹿脖子
just run out
就是用盡廢退
this means
這個就是說
Come to agree. From this point of view, I agree.
來贊成 從這個角度來講我贊成
creation theory
創造論就
If there is a word, it is impossible for you to be more difficult
有話就是你一下不可能比較難
I have no idea
我不知道
I think
我覺得
We are so complicated now alone
我們現在一個人這麼的複雜
You said you want to start with the original one
你說要從原始的那個
maybe tens of thousands of years
可能幾萬年
I think it's a little difficult
我是覺得有一點難
I find it difficult
我是覺得有點難
I think it's almost time
我想時間也差不多了
Our other postcards must be given to Mr. Zhao
我們那個其他明信片都要給趙老師
good
好
I'm just curious, that's what
我是很好奇就是說那個
in that
在那個
Infertility
自交不清合
Can
可以
infertile hybrid
自交不清合雜交
And that self-pollinating hand
還有那個自化受粉手
In the process of pollen hall formation
在花粉館形成的過程裡面
What would be the difference in those lead substances
那些引導物質的差異會是什麼
OK
OK
Self-incompatibility of Baozi body
包子體的自交不清合性
is the so-called
就是所謂的
Because the so-called incompatible thing
因為所謂造成自交不清合的東西
on the surface of pollen grains
是在花粉粒的表面
The surface of the pollen grain is from
花粉粒的表面是從
So-called
所謂的
flowers are coming
就是花要來的
So the one where the flower will come is a diploid
所以花要來的那個是屬於兩倍體
So it's bun body
所以是包子體
The gametophyte is indistinct
那配子體不清合是說
When the pollen house the gamete grows in the pistil
當花粉館這個配子長在池蕊
Inside, this is the configuration body
裡面的時候這是配置體
what about this time
那這時候呢
From its suffix, it will be clear that it is called SRNS
從它的詞尾會分明一個叫SRNS
This goes into the pollen tube of the plant
這個它會進到植物的花粉管的裡面
This SRNS will put the Mission-9NS inside
這SRNS會把裡面的Mission-9NS
so7RNA
所以7RNA
All of these RNAs are kneeled down
所有這些的RNA都被跪掉
So it has no way to cause
所以它就沒有辦法造成
Another one is the so-called
另外還有一個就是所謂的就是
Jia Riko
賈里子
Not Kelson
不是Kelson
some have one another
有一些有一個是另外一個
in the so-called self-infertility
是在所謂的自交不進而行
Also the pollen tubes are on the inside
也是花粉管在裡面上
but it caused
但是它所造成的
No, this is Jia Lizi
不是這個是賈里子
That lid makes it impossible to get in
那個蓋里子讓它沒有辦法進去
so the whole later
所以整個後來
The entire pollen tube cannot grow
整個花粉管就沒辦法成長
So the mechanism is slightly different
所以機制是稍微有點不太一樣
OK, I'll just NAS
好 我就NAS一下
The next trial
下一次的試想驗示
December 17th
12月17號
Hu Shi
事實上是胡適
We have a lecture by Dean Gu
我們有一個顧院長的講座
It is a popular science lecture given by President Gu of Hu Shi
是胡適的顧院長的科普講座
that's from the Institute of History and
那是歷史與研究所的
Lecture by Wang Hongtai Research Institute
王鴻泰研究院主講
From Ximenqing to Jiabaoying
從西門慶到加保鷹
Feminist Review and Emotional Evolution with the People of the Ming and Qing Dynasties
與明清世人的女色評審與情感演化
very different subject
非常不是不一樣的題目
These grids are for everyone to participate in
這些網格就各位才能參加
next science talk
下一次的科普演講
Well, we thank Dr. Gao Guangyu, Gao Guang Researcher
好 我們謝謝高光玉博士的高光研究員
"Female Reviews and Emotional Actors in the Ming and Qing Dynasties"
《明清世人的女色評審與情感演員》